<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A defence of the Protestant Christian religion against popery: in answer to A discourse of a Roman Catholick Wherein the manifold apostaties, heresies, and schisms of the chruch of Rome, as also, the weakness of her pretensions from the scriptures and the fathers, are briefly laid open: by an English Protestant.</title>
            <author>Mather, Samuel, 1626-1671.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1672</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 148 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 32 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A50252</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing M1278</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R217670</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99829325</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99829325</idno>
            <idno type="VID">33762</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A50252)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 33762)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1918:7)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A defence of the Protestant Christian religion against popery: in answer to A discourse of a Roman Catholick Wherein the manifold apostaties, heresies, and schisms of the chruch of Rome, as also, the weakness of her pretensions from the scriptures and the fathers, are briefly laid open: by an English Protestant.</title>
                  <author>Mather, Samuel, 1626-1671.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 56 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Dublin :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Printed in the year, M.DC.LXXII. [1672]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Place of publication from Wing.</note>
                  <note>Ascribed to Samuel Mather by Wing. An English Protestant = Samuel Mather. "Advertisements to the reader" signed S.M.</note>
                  <note>Caption title on B1 reads: A discourse of a Roman Catholick. Caption title on C2 reads: A defence of the Protestant Christian religion against Popery.</note>
                  <note>Running titles read: "A discourse of a Roman Catholick" and "A defence of the Protestant Christian religion against Popery".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catholic Church --  Ireland --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Religion --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Protestants --  Ireland --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Anti-Catholicism --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:33762:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:33762:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A DEFENCE <hi>Of the Proteſtant Chriſtian Religion againſt</hi> POPERY: In Anſwer to a Diſcourſe of a <hi>Roman Catholick.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>WHEREIN The Manifold Apoſtaſies, Hereſies, and Schiſms of the Church of <hi>ROME,</hi> as alſo, the Weakneſs of Her Pretenſions from the Scriptures and the Fathers, are briefly Laid open:</p>
            <p>By an Engliſh Proteſtant.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Frederic. Secundus Germ. Imp.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Roma</hi> diu titubans, longis Erroribus acta</l>
                  <l>Corruet, ac Mundi deſinet eſſe Caput.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>In Hereſies long Chace,</hi> Rome <hi>ſtumbling ſhall</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Loſe the Worlds Headſhip, and to Ruine fall.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
            </q>
            <p>Printed in the YEAR, M.DC.LXXII.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:33762:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:33762:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:33762:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:33762:3"/>
            <head>Advertiſements TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>IT is thought needleſs to trouble the Reader with a Narrative of the Tranſactions, or with Copies of the Letters that have paſſed about this Affair, or with the Names of the Perſons concerned therein; or laſtly, with the Motives and Providen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces which have invited in this juncture of time, to the publiſhing <hi>this Defence of our Religion againſt Popery.</hi> The <hi>Romaniſts</hi> Diſcourſe is prefixed and publiſhed wholly and intirely by it ſelf, over and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide what is repeated of it in the Anſwer. To the Anſwer there be ſome Additions, for the <hi>Readers</hi> fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther help, and for the further illuſtration of ſome things; a brief intimation whereof, might be preſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med ſufficient to the <hi>Romaniſt</hi> himſelf, he being one of their Learned men in Holy Orders amongſt them. And whereas the <hi>Author</hi> of this Anſwer and Defence, in a Letter to the perſon that called him to this Work, did together with it, expreſs his own Sentiments thereof, it is judged convenient, inſtead of any further <hi>Preface,</hi> to communicate them out of the ſaid Letter, wherein he ſaith:
<floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <p>
                        <hi>I Have received your Letter, and I have peruſed Mr.</hi> K. <hi>his Diſcourſe, which he challengeth our Divines to Anſwer. And whereas you have pitcht
<pb facs="tcp:33762:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>upon me to do it, becauſe (as your Letter Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſeth) being the Cauſe of God, you durſt not Truſt it in every hand: As I have reaſon to acknowledge the great reſpect and value you are pleaſed to put upon me, ſo withall I muſt needs own my own unwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thineſs and inſufficiency for this, or any other good word or work. It is free Grace I have been de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pending and looking up unto for help, from whence alone I have had it; and it is the ſame free Grace that muſt bleſs what is ſaid, and bring it home with power. I have ſent you herewith an Anſwer to his Paper. The Civilities you have done to him (which I ſee himſelf in his Letter to you doth ingenuonſly ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge) may tend, I hope, to let him ſee. That it is our Religion to do good to all, and that we deſire to do good Works, though not to be juſtified by them. Let me have a part in your Remembrances at the Throne of Grace, to which I Recommend you and yours; which is all, at preſent, from</hi>
                     </p>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>Your moſt humble Servant in the Lord, <hi>S. M.</hi>
                        </signed>
                        <dateline>
                           <hi>DVBLIN,</hi> 
                           <date>July ult. 1670.</date>
                        </dateline>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:33762:4"/>
            <head>A Diſcourſe OF A <hi>ROMAN CATHOLICK:</hi> Of the one, onely, and ſingular onely one Catholick, and Roman Faith.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>ONe Lord, one Faith, one Baptiſm, one God and Father of all, who is over all, and through all, and in us all,</q>
               <bibl>Eph. 4.5, 6. Malac. 2.10.</bibl>
               <q>Firſt I give thanks to my God, through Jeſus Chriſt for you all, for that your faith is manifeſted in all the world,</q>
               <bibl>Rom. 1.8.</bibl>
               <q>I deſire alſo to ſee you, that I may impart unto you of ſpiritual grace to confirm you, that is to ſay, to be together comforted in you, which together is your faith and mine,</q>
               <bibl>ibid v. 11. &amp; 12.</bibl>
               <q>That now we may not be children, wavering up and down, and carried about with every wind of doctrine in the wickedneſs of men, in deceit, to the circumvention of errour,</q>
               <bibl>Epheſ. 4.14.</bibl>
               <q>Be not carried with various and ſtrange doctrines, for it is a very good grace to ſettle the heart,</q>
               <bibl>Hebr. 13.9.</bibl>
               <q>Alſo I do not pray for them only, but likewiſe for theſe which will believe through their word in me, that all may be one, as your Father and I, and I in you, that alſo they in us may be one, that the world may believe that you ſent me,</q>
               <bibl>Joan. 17. ver. 20.</bibl>
            </epigraph>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:33762:5"/>
            <p>Now, I hope, it will not be deemed, but that the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> was once a moſt pure, excellent, flouriſhing, and Mother Church, <hi>ut ſupra,</hi> Rom. 1.</p>
            <p>This Church could not ceaſe to be ſo, but ſhe muſt fail either by Apoſtaſie, Hereſie, or Schiſm, <hi>Rom.</hi> 16.17.</p>
            <p>
               <list>
                  <item n="1">I. <hi>Apoſtaſie is not only a renouncing of the Faith of Chriſt, but the very name and title of Chriſtianity; no man will ſay, that the Church of</hi> Rome <hi>had ever ſuch a fall, or fell thus.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item n="2">II. <hi>Hereſie is an adheſion to ſome private and ſingular Opinion or Error in Faith, contrary to the general and approved Doctrine of the Church.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item n="3">III. <hi>If the Church of</hi> Rome <hi>did ever adhere to any ſingular, or new Opinion, diſagreeable to the common re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived Doctrine?</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Firſt,</hi> I pray ſatisfie me as to theſe particulars, <hi>viz.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item n="4">IV. <hi>By what general Council was it ever condemn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed?</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item n="5">V. <hi>Which of the Fathers ever wrote againſt Her?</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item n="6">VI. <hi>Or by what Authority was ſhe ever Reproved? for it ſeems to me very incongruous, that ſo great a Church ſhould be condemned by every one that hath a wind to condemn Her.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item n="7">VII. <hi>Schiſm is a departure or diviſion from the V<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity of the Church, whereby the band and communion held with ſome former Church, is broken and diſſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item n="8">VIII. <hi>If ever the Church of</hi> Rome <hi>divided Her ſelf by Schiſm, from any other body of faithful
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:33762:5"/>Chriſtians, or brake communion, or went forth from the ſociety of any elder Church, I pray ſatisfie your ſelf and me to theſe particulars.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item n="9">IX. <hi>Firſt, Whoſe company did ſhe leave? Secondly, from what body did ſhe go forth?</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item n="10">X. <hi>Where was the true Church which ſhe forſook? for it appears not a little ſtrange to me, That a Church ſhould be accounted Schiſmatical, when there cannot be aſſigned any other Church different from Her (which from Age to Age ſince Chriſts time, hath continued vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible) from whom ſhe departed,</hi> &amp;c.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Concluſion. <hi>If the Catholick</hi> Roman <hi>Church was once the true Church, ſhe ſtill remained ſo; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they who have departed from Her, are departed from the true Church, and ſo are out of the way,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>The uſual colour of believing more or leſs than the Church alloweth, is vain and erroneous, inaſmuch as that very Chriſt which ſtored Her with knowledge of Gods revealed Truth, and with power to convey the ſame, hath alſo endued Her with inerrability to convey the ſame juſtly, without danger of miſcarry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, againſt Iguorance.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>Mat. 13. 11.</bibl> To you it is given to know the myſteries of heaven.</q>
            <q>
               <bibl>Mat. 5.14.</bibl> 
               <hi>Againſt darkneſs,</hi> you are the light of the world.</q>
            <q>
               <bibl>John 14.16.</bibl> 
               <hi>Againſt error and falſhood:</hi> I will ſend unto you the Spirit of truth, to remain with you for ever.</q>
            <q>
               <bibl>1 Tim 3.</bibl> 
               <hi>Againſt weakneſs:</hi> She is the pillar and ground of truth.</q>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:33762:6"/>
            <q>
               <bibl>Mat. 16.18.</bibl> Hell gates ſhall not prevail againſt her; <hi>to make which good, Chriſt called his eternal Father to his aid, prayed him, and was heard for his reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence.</hi>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>Mat. 28.20.</bibl> Behold I am with you all dayes to the end of the world.</q>
            <p>Therefore if they charge the Catholick <hi>Roman</hi> Church with Error, they muſt ſay, that either Chriſt was not of power to keep his Church from ſtraying, or that he wanted fidelity to make good his word.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>Mat. 5.14.</bibl> You are the light of the world. A City that is ſet on an hill cannot be hid.</q>
            <q>
               <bibl>Mat. 16.19.</bibl> Whatſoever thou ſhalt bind on earth, ſhall be bound in heaven.</q>
            <p>I pray name me the Church that was commonly counted the true Chriſtian Church, in which you re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mained, and from which you are not departed.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Mat.</hi> 16.18. The Church cannot fail being builded upon a Rock, nor needs no new Maſons to rebuild her again.</p>
            <p>1 Tim. 4.1. St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>Certain will depart from the faith. They went from us.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Whether did the <hi>Roman</hi> Church go from any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther known Church, or did any other go from her? Satisfie your ſelf and me, in this, I pray you.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:33762:6"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>Teſtimonies of the Fathers, for the See of</hi> Rome.</head>
               <p>THe Names of the Twelve Apoſtles are theſe, the firſt <hi>Simon,</hi> who is called <hi>Peter,</hi> &amp;c. In which place, Divine <hi>Epiphanius</hi> ſaith,
<note place="margin">De <hi>Epiph. in Ancoratu.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>That God knew the thoughts of hearts, knoweth alſo who is worthy to be placed in the firſt place; he hath choſen</hi> Peter, <hi>that he might be the Head of his Diſeiples.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>St. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſaith of <hi>Peters</hi> Succeſſors,
<note place="margin">De <hi>Aug. con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra Epiſt.</hi> Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menioni. L. 1. c. 2.</note> 
                  <hi>to the ſitting in the Chair of the</hi> Roman <hi>Church, the whole Chriſtian world is ſubject.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Alſo <hi>Auguſtine</hi> elſewhere:
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Aug.</hi> Epiſt. 162.</note> 
                  <hi>In the</hi> Roman <hi>Church alwayes flouriſhed the Sovereignty of the Apoſtolical Chair.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The ſame in another place, <hi>Number</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>the Prieſts of that ſame ſeat of St.</hi> Peter, <hi>and ſee which of the Fathers ſucceed him; for he is the Rock which the proud gates of Hell do not overcome.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>St. <hi>Ambroſe,</hi> Rome (ſaith he) <hi>hath the principali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of Apoſtolical Prieſthood.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:33762:7"/>
            <head>The Contents.</head>
            <list>
               <item>CHAP. I. <hi>Proving, That a true viſible Church may fall away.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>CHAP. II. <hi>Of the Nature and kinds of Apoſtaſie, and of the Apoſtaſies of the Church of</hi> Rome.</item>
               <item>CHAP. III. <hi>Of the Nature of Hereſie.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>CHAP. IV. <hi>Of the Hereſies of the Church of</hi> Rome, <hi>eight particulars inſtanced.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>CHAP. V. <hi>Of the Nature of Schiſm, and of the Schiſous of the Church of</hi> Rome, <hi>both within her ſelf, and from other Churches.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>CHAP. VI. <hi>Some places of Scripture for the inerra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility of the Church of</hi> Rome, <hi>anſwered.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>CHAP. VII. <hi>Of humane Teſtimonies for, and againſt the Church of</hi> Rome.</item>
               <item>CHAP. VIII. <hi>An Appendix for the further illuſtration of ſome things which are but briefly hinted in the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer</hi> Chapters.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:33762:7"/>
            <head>A DEFENCE <hi>Of the Proteſtant Chriſtian Religion againſt</hi> POPERY: In Anſwer to a Diſcourſe, Intituled, [Of the one, onely, and ſingular onely one Catholick, and Roman Faith.]</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. I. <hi>Proving, That a true viſible Church may fall away.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TO paſs by the Rhetorick of the Title, and the aptneſs of the phraſe of [<hi>ſingular onely one</hi>] as an emphatical addition to [<hi>the one onely</hi>] and the conſiſtence between <hi>Roman,</hi> and <hi>Catholick,</hi> and between <hi>ſingular,</hi> and <hi>Catholick,</hi> or <hi>univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal.</hi> How, and in what reſpects of reaſon, and what ſenſes may be thought upon, wherein the ſame thing may be called both <hi>Roman</hi> and <hi>Catholick,</hi> both <hi>ſingular</hi> and <hi>univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal.</hi> The Diſcourſe it ſelf begins with unconuected Quotations of ſeveral choice portions of Holy Scripture: And, indeed, ſo far as there is a cordial adherence and ſubjection of heart unto that rule among different parties and perſuaſions, it will, through the grace of Chriſt, produce either union of Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, or at leaſt union of Brotherly affection, and forbearance of love; but what eſteem the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> hath for the
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:33762:8"/>Holy Scriptures, is well known, She doth not ſubject her <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> unto them: And though you in this Diſcourſe de Quote them, as your Writers ſometimes do; yet, if you be a true <hi>Roman Catholick,</hi> it is not with any intent to ſubject your Church up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Scripture, and to advance the Scriptures above your Church; but onely to deal with Hereticks (as you call them) at their own Weapons; and to uſe the Scripture as a ſtepping<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone, whereby to mount up your Church into the Throne of her pretended Supremacy and Inerrability, as one would uſe a ſtirrup to get into the ſaddle; wherein, nevertheleſs, your means hath an inconſiſtency with your end, as will further appear, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we come to a cloſe of this Debate: Your Argumentation from the Scriptures you recite, begins thus.</p>
               <div type="discourse">
                  <head>DISCOURSE.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Now, I hope, it will not be deemed, but that the Church of</hi> Rome <hi>was once a moſt pure, excellent, flouriſhing, and Mother-Church,</hi> ut ſupra, <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="answer">
                  <head>ANSWER.</head>
                  <p>It will not be denyed, but is readily granted by us, That there was once a True Church in <hi>Rome;</hi> that is, a Congregati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of ſaithful men, wherein the pure Word of God was Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched, and the Sacraments duly miniſtred, according to the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance of Chriſt, which is the deſcription of the viſible Church in the <hi>Thirty nine Articles.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Artic.</hi> 19.</note> And that this Church which was in <hi>Rome,</hi> might be inſtrumental (as Churches in populous Cities often are) to propagate the Faith, and plant Churches in other places, is not improbable: But that ſhe had any ſuperlative Purity, or any motherly Power and Authority, over and above other Churches, is part of the thing in Queſtion between her and us.</p>
                  <p>The Church of <hi>Corinth,</hi> the Church of <hi>Epheſus,</hi> of <hi>Theſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenica,</hi> of <hi>Smyrna,</hi> of <hi>Philadelphia,</hi> were once pure, flouriſhing Churches, as well as the Church of <hi>Rome.</hi> What may be truly ſaid of her, may be truly ſaid of all other Goſpel Churches, in their firſt plantation and conſtitution by the Apoſtles; yet, it doth not follow, That ever they were Mother-Churches in your ſenſe, or, that becauſe they were pure at firſt, that therefore they are ſo ſtill; for viſible Churches may degenerate, and apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtatize,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:33762:8"/>though the Myſtical Church, that is, ſuch as are in Chriſt by the spirit of ſaving Faith, cannot wholly fall off from him, yet ſuch as are in him onely by external and viſible profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion may: <hi>Jer.</hi> 2.21. <hi>I had planted thee a noble vine, wholly a right ſeed; how then art thou turned into the degenerate plant of a ſtrange vine unto me? How is the faithful City become an Harlot? It was full of judgment, righteouſneſs lodged in it, but now mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therers,</hi> Iſa. 1.:21. Whereupon a Church thus forſaking God, God may forſake them. He may diſcovenant and un-church a people, and give them a Bill of Divorce, and withdraw the ſigns and tokens of his love and preſence. He may <hi>break the ſtaffe of beauty, and cut it aſunder,</hi> that he may <hi>break the Covenant he hath made with all the people.</hi> He may alſo <hi>break the other ſtaffe of bands and brotherhood between</hi> Judah <hi>and</hi> Iſrael, <hi>Zach.</hi> 11.10, 14. He may give them a Bill of Divorce, <hi>Jer.</hi> 3.8. <hi>When for all the cauſes whereby back-ſliding</hi> Iſrael <hi>committed Adultery, I had put her away, and given her a bill of divorce; yet her treacherous ſiſter</hi> Judah, <hi>feared not.</hi> God may ſay unto a people <hi>Le-ruhamab</hi> and <hi>Lo-ammi, I will no more have mercy upon the houſe of</hi> Iſrael; <hi>for ye are not my people and I will not be your God,</hi> Hoſ. 1.6. <hi>Plead with your mother, plead: for ſhe is not my wife, neither am I her husband,</hi> Hoſ. 2.2. God may <hi>remove the candleſtick out of its place,</hi> Rev. 2.5.</p>
                  <p>You ſee in all theſe Scriptures, what the Lord hath threatned and done to other Churches in dayes of old; which, as it ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly overthrows any ſuch imagination, That a True Church cannot fall away; ſo it ſhews, That your Church claims ſuch a priviledge, as never any Church enjoyed: <hi>Go to</hi> Shiloh, <hi>where I ſet my name at firſt,</hi> Jer. 7.12, 14. Go to <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and ſee what God hath done unto it for the wickedneſs of his people <hi>Iſrael:</hi> Never any Church enjoyed ſuch a priviledge as yours pretend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth to, of Indefectibility and Impoſſibility of loſing their Church eſtate and priviledges. It was Chriſts own threatning to the <hi>Jewes, The kingdom of God ſhall be taken from you, and given to a Nation bringing forth the fruits thereof,</hi> Matth. 21.43.</p>
                  <p>Yea, the Lord hath denounced the like: Threatnings, and brandiſhed the ſame flaming Sword againſt the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> in particular, and that from this very inſtance and example of the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Church before mentioned, <hi>Kem.</hi> 11.17, 18, 19, 20, 21, 22. <hi>And if ſome of the branches were broken off, and thou being,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:33762:9"/>a wild Olive tree wert graſſed in among them, Boaſt not againſt the branches;</hi> which your Church doth againſt all the Churches in the World, pretending to ſuch tranſcendent priviledges and prerogatives above all other Siſter-Churches: <hi>But if thou boaſt, thou beareſt not the root, but the root thee. Thou wilt ſay, the bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches were broken off, that I might be graffed in: Well, becauſe of unbelief, they were broken off, and thou ſtandeſt by faith. Be not high-minded, but fear.</hi> This is written to Her, that ſaith, <hi>She cannot erre: For if God ſpared not the natural branches, take heed leſt be alſo ſpare not thee. Behold therefore the goodneſs, and ſeverity of God: on them which fell, ſeverity; but towards thee, goodneſs, if thou continue in his goodneſs: otherwiſe thou alſo ſhalt be out off.</hi> You ſee he threatneth Her with cutting off; And he hath execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted theſe his righteous Threatnings, becauſe She hath not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued in his goodneſs, therefore he hath cut Her off, and given Her a bill of Divorce, having declared Her in the Scriptures of Truth to be <hi>Babylon,</hi> and Her Head <hi>Antichriſt,</hi> even <hi>Babylan the Great, the Mother of Harlots, a monſtrous Beaſt, the principal object of all the vyals of his wrath.</hi> And her Head, <hi>a falſe Prophet, a Star fullen from Heaven, a perſecuting Horn, wearing out the Saints of the moſt High,</hi> as it is written in theſe, and the like Scriptures: <hi>Daniel</hi> 7. and <hi>Dan. cap.</hi> 11. <hi>verſ.</hi> 36, &amp;c. 2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 2. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.1, &amp;c. And it is the chief ſcope of the Book of the <hi>Revelation,</hi> to diſcover and reveal <hi>Antichriſt,</hi> in every <hi>Chapter,</hi> from the ſixth, to the twentieth. This is ſomething that doth ſome way con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern this great Apoſtaſie; in all which Scriptures, both of the Old and New Teſtament, She may read, as it were, the Letters of her Divorce: The Lord, who was Her Husband, having publiſhed them, and left them upon Record to all the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, that they may take notice that She is not his Wife, nor he Her husband; and that they may do as is written, <hi>Revel.</hi> 18 4. <hi>Come out of her my people, that ye be not partakers, of her ſins, and that ye receive not of bet plagues.</hi> And accordingly we, for our parts, in obedience to this command, have proteſted againſt Her, and are come out from Her; and our defence muſt be with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſhifts and ſubterfuges, by making good the charge againſt Her. What can She ſay for Her ſelf? How will She clear and vindicate Her ſelf from all this fin and ſhame? You attempt it under three Heads, of <hi>Apoſtaſic, Hareſie,</hi> and <hi>Schiſm;</hi> and I muſt follow you in your own method, though it be none of the beſt:
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:33762:9"/>But whether you took your Diſcourſes hereof out of <hi>Fiat Lux,</hi> for there they are <hi>verbatim,</hi> there is more than a meer coincidence of matter, or that <hi>Fiat Lux</hi> had learned them privately from you, and then publiſhed them in Print, ſuppreſſing your name, I leave it to him and you to diſpute that point, and to your infallible Judge to determine it, and judge between you: Both he and you ſpeak thus.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. II. <hi>Of the Nature and Kinds of Apoſtaſie, and of the Apoſtaſies of the Church of</hi> Rome.</head>
               <div type="discourse">
                  <head>DISCOURSE.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>This Church could not ceaſe to be ſo, but She muſt fall either by Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaſie, Hereſie, or Schiſm.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="answer">
                  <head>ANSWER.</head>
                  <p>THis Enumeration is very defective and confuſed, in that it makes Apoſtaſie one particular <hi>ſpecies,</hi> or kind of fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling away, whereas Apoſtaſie, and falling away, is the ſame thing; the one being a Greek word, and the other Engliſh: for Apoſtaſie is contrary to the True Chriſtian Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, which is the tying of man to God again (from <hi>re,</hi> and <hi>li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>go</hi>) after his fall in the bonds of Faith and Love, or obedience of Love. The Scripture everywhere makes theſe the two parts of True Religion: 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.13. <hi>Hold faſt the form of ſound words which thou haſt heard of me, in faith and love, which is in Chriſt Jeſus.</hi> 1 Tim. 3.9. <hi>Holding the myſtery of the faith in a pure conſcience.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Hence therefore there be two wayes of Apoſtaſie, <hi>viz.</hi> either from the Faith of the Goſpel by fundamental ignorance, and he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſie, and unbelief, or from Goſpel-obedience, which is as large as the rule thereof; of which <hi>David</hi> ſaith, <hi>Thy Commandments are exceeding broad,</hi> Pſal. 119.96. Therefore under this head comes Idolatry, Superſtition, Schiſm, Witchcraft, Perjury, Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:33762:10"/>Sedition, Murther, Whoredom, Theft, Equivocation, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Men may Apoſtatize, and fa'l away from God, <hi>by making ſhipwrack of the faith, and by putting away a good conſcience,</hi> 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.19. The Apoſtle ſpeaks of ſome, <hi>who profeſs they know God; but in werks they deny him, being abominable, and diſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedient, and unto every good work reprobate,</hi> Titus. 1.16.</p>
                  <p>But this kind of Apoſtaſie by evil works, and ſcandalous ſins, is omitted and forgotten, which is another Error in your diſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bution; though it is that which your Church, and Popes, are deeply guilty of, notwithſtanding all your boaſtings of your good works, and merits, and ſupererogations with God. The ſixth Trumpet inſtanceth in <hi>Idolatries, Murthers, Sorceries, Fornicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, Thefts,</hi> as Sins that do abound among you, <hi>Revel.</hi> 9. <hi>ult.</hi> And all Hiſtories bear witneſs to it. The corruption of Life, as well as Doctrine, was ſo great, before the Proteſtant Reformation; ſo many the offences, abuſes, and ſcandals; and ſuch the degene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated notoriety of them, that as it was the common deſire of Sober men in <hi>Luthers</hi> time, that there might be a free and ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Council, in order to a general Reformation of the Church, which all men obſerved to be wofully degenerated: So there were Nine Select Cardinals and Prelates of your own Church,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ſil. Delect. Card. &amp; Praed. De Emendanda Eccleſia.</hi> Ann. 1538. See the Appendix, <hi>cap.</hi> 8.</note> who did privately adviſe the Pope to Reform things amiſs, in a Paper they preſented to him, he having asked their Advice; wherein they do attaque the very Popes themſelves, as the Heads of the Apoſtaſie, and Fountains of Corruption to the whole Church. <hi>Principium horum malorum vide fuiſſe, quod nonnulli Pontifices tui Praedeceſſores prurientes auribus,</hi> &amp;c. Wherein they do their Popes no wrong, for they ſpeak no worſe of them, then your own Hiſtorians repreſent them, nor then Pope <hi>Adrian</hi> the Sixth did acknowledge them to be. In his Inſtructions to his Legate <hi>Cheregatus,</hi> and in his Letter to the Princes of <hi>Germany,</hi> Aſſembled in the Imperial Dyet at <hi>Norimberge,</hi> 1523. He ſaith, <hi>S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>imus in hac ſede aliquot jam annis multa abominanda fuiſſe,
<note place="margin">Fox's Acts and Mon. <hi>Vol.</hi> 2. pag. 78. <hi>Lampad. Mel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lif. Hiſtor.</hi> Part. 3. pag. 425.</note> abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus in ſpiritualibus exceſſus in mandatis, &amp; omnia denique in perver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſum mutata—Se quidem non ignorare quid Scriptura docet, nempe à Sacerdotibus populi iniquitatis originem ſcaturire,—&amp; ab ipſoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pite Pontificio malum diffiuere in membra inferiora.</hi> There have been, <hi>ſaith he,</hi> many years, many Abominations in this See, Abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes in Spirituals, Exceſſes in Commands, and all things perverſly ordered.—The Fountain of Iniquity hath flowed from the
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:33762:10"/>Prieſts to the people, as the Scripture ſaith; and from the Pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tificial Head, the evil hath flowed into the inferiour members. Thus he, who, as you ſay, could not erre in judgment. <hi>If a man would chooſe a Religion on purpoſe for the gratifying of his luſts,</hi> Sir <hi>Walter Raleigh</hi> ſaith, <hi>He knows none like Popery.</hi> You have ſo many wayes to diſpenſe with your Conſciences, and to indulge Sinners a licentious liberty to take their ſwinge in their luſts. Your laſt ſwarm of Locuſts, the Jeſuites, have made it their bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs to corrupt all Morality, as is to be ſeen at large, in the Book called, <hi>The Myſtery of Jeſuitiſm.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Moreover, there is yet a third overſight in your Enumeration over and above both the former; for as a Church which was once true and pure, may ceaſe to be ſo, by ſuch backſlidings as have been inſtanced on her part, ſo ſhe may ceaſe to be at all by righteous and deſtroying Judgments on Gods part; which is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo the caſe of the Old Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> Providence having cut them off by the Sword of the <hi>Goths</hi> and <hi>Vandals,</hi> and other Northern Nations, about 400 years after Chriſt, as he did the ten Tribes by the <hi>Aſſyrians</hi> of old; and he hath ſubſtituted another people and language in their Land and place, <hi>viz.</hi> thoſe we call <hi>Italians,</hi> as he did the <hi>Samaritans</hi> in the Land of <hi>Iſrael:</hi> And as then, ſo now, the Succeſſors are worſe, and further off from God, than their degenerate Predeceſſors, whom they ſaw the Lord deſtroy and cut off before their eyes. Now ſuppoſe the <hi>Sama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritans</hi> of old had pleaded a Plea not unlike yours, <hi>viz.</hi> thus: The <hi>Iſraelites</hi> were a true, famous, flouriſhing Church in the dayes of <hi>Moſes,</hi> and <hi>Joſhuah;</hi> and in the dayes of <hi>David,</hi> and <hi>Solomon,</hi> therefore we <hi>Samaritans</hi> are ſo now. The Anſwer is eaſie, You are neither of the ſame Religion, no, nor yet ſo much as the ſame people; for they were <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> but ye <hi>Samaritans.</hi> So here, What though there was in the dayes of <hi>Paul</hi> a Goſpel Church of <hi>Romans</hi> at <hi>Rome,</hi> though ſo far as appears not very great or numerous in thoſe dayes; but that ever there was ſuch a Church of <hi>Samaritans</hi> or <hi>Italians</hi> there, a pure Church there ſince the <hi>Roman</hi> people were cut off, and their Language ceaſed, to be a Mother-tongue, and the <hi>Italian</hi> came in place, <hi>Hoe tibi incumbit demonſtrandum,</hi> prove this if you can. Alas, the True Church is dead, and gone from thence above 1000 years ago, and a monſtrons Beaſt with Ten crowned Horns is riſen up in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead thereof: But you proceed to the firſt Head of your Diſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bution, thus.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="discourse">
                  <pb n="14" facs="tcp:33762:11"/>
                  <head>DISCOURSE.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Apoſtaſie is not only a Renouncing of the Faith of Chriſt, but of the very Name and Title of Chriſtianity. No man will ſay, That the Church of</hi> Rome <hi>bad ever ſuch a fall, or fell thus.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="answer">
                  <head>ANSWER.</head>
                  <p>You thus reſtrain the word <hi>Apoſtaſie</hi> to the groſſeſt, and dee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſt degree thereof, that ſo you may the better defend your Church from the guilt of this ſin: But there is no neceſſity ſo to reſtrain it; for there may be deep Apoſtaſie from God, under a name and outſide profeſſion of Religion. It is written of the Church of <hi>Sardis,</hi> Revel. 3.1. <hi>Thou haſt a name that thou liveſt, but art dead.</hi> Neither the Scripture, nor the original ſignifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Greek word, <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, which ſignifies <hi>a falling a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way;</hi> nor the common and ordinary uſe of it, requires that there be in it, a Renouncing of the very Name and Title of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity. It is uſed in ſundry places of Scripture, where no ſuch Reſtraint is intimated, as <hi>Acts.</hi> 21.21. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, <hi>Thou teacheſt the Jews to forſake</hi> Moſes. And concerning Antichriſt, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.1. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, <hi>Some ſhall apoſtatize, or depart from the faith.</hi> And again, 2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 2.3. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, <hi>except there come a falling away firſt.</hi> And, <hi>ver.</hi> 7. This Apoſtaſie is called, <hi>A Myſtery of Iniquity.</hi> Therefore it ſhall not be an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen, total, profeſſed Apoſtaſie, but partial, and palliated over with fair umbrages, and plauſible pretenſions, elſe why is it cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, <hi>A Myſtery of Iniquity, and Myſtical</hi> Babylon? Nor do you indeed your own ſelves, alwayes uſe the word Apoſtaſie onely in that groſs ſenſe; for you ſcruple not to beſtow the title of Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate, as well as Heretick, upon <hi>Luther,</hi> and the Proteſtant Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches; though neither he, nor we, ever did, nor through grace, ever will Renounce the Name and Title of Chriſtianity.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Cyprian,</hi> warning the Saints, and people of God, in his time, to take heed of ſpiritual and ſitbtile Deluſions,
<note place="margin">Cypr. <hi>De <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>
                           <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitate Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fia.</hi>
                     </note> open and profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed perſecution being not their only danger: He ſheweth, how Sathan perceiving, that by the large diffuſion, and ſpreading of Goſpel-light, <hi>Pagan</hi> Idolatry, and their Temples were much for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaken: <hi>Excogitavit novam fraudem, ut ſub ipſo Chriſtiani nominis titulo fallat Incautos:</hi> He hath bethought himſelf of a new de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit, whereby to miſlead unwary Souls; under the very Name, and Title of Chriſtianity. <hi>Sathan</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>transforming him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:33762:11"/>into an Angel of light, and ſuborning his Miniſters, as Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of righteouſneſs, bringing night for day,</hi> Antichriſtum, ſub vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cabulo Chriſti. <hi>Antichriſt, under the name of Chriſt.</hi> The Church of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> in the time of her Apoſtaſie, did not Renounce the very Name and Title of <hi>Jehovah;</hi> but they <hi>did worſhip, and ſwear by the Lord, and by</hi> Malcham <hi>too,</hi> Zephan. 1.5. So thoſe mungrel <hi>Samaritans,</hi> 2 Kings 17.33, 41. <hi>They profeſſed,</hi> Ezra. 4.2. <hi>We ſeek your God, as you do;</hi> as fair a pretenſion as any your Church can make: And in Chriſts time, they had ſome confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed notions and expectations of the Meſſiah, <hi>John</hi> 4.29. They had learned to ſay, <hi>our father Jacob,</hi> as well as you can ſay <hi>Saint Peter,</hi> John. 4.12.</p>
                  <p>So in like manner the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> though She hath not Renounced the very Name and Title of Chriſtianity, yet She is deeply guilty of Apoſtaſie from God, divers other wayes, both in her Head and Members; She is, and may be called an Apoſtate Church, as having fallen away from the Faith and Doctrine of the Goſpel, by fundamental Unbelief, Ignorance and Herefie, and from Goſpel obedience, by the moſt abominable profaneneſs of life, by the groſſeſt kind of ſins, and ſcandals againſt all the Ten Commandments; concerning which, you prudently forbear to ſay any thing, but concerning the former head, <hi>viz. Apoſtaſie from the Faith:</hi> Your Defence is this.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. III. <hi>Of the Nature of Hereſie.</hi>
               </head>
               <div type="discourse">
                  <head>DISCOURSE.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Hereſie is an adbeſion to ſome private, and ſingular Opinion, or Error in Faith, contrary to the general and approved Doctrine of the Church. If</hi> Rome <hi>did ever adhere to any ſuch Opinion,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>By what Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Council was it ever condemned? Which of the Fathers ever wrote againſt Her? Or by what Authority was She ever Repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved?</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="answer">
                  <pb n="16" facs="tcp:33762:12"/>
                  <head>ANSWER.</head>
                  <p>This Deſcription of Hereſie, and the Queries grounded there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon, as they are not agreeable, either to the Scriptural, or Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſtical ſenſe, and uſe of the Word; ſo they are indeed no better than a begging of the thing in queſtion between you and us: For you know we hold, That the Rule whereby to judge of Hereſie, is the Scripture, and not the Opinions of Churches, of Fathers,
<note place="margin">Mr. <hi>Gales</hi> Idea <hi>of Janſeniſm Hiſtor. &amp; dog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mat.</hi> Part. 2. Sect. 28. p. 157.</note> or Councils. <hi>Tertullian</hi> makes it the Badge of an Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick to decline the Scriptures; he ſaith, They are <hi>Noctue &amp; Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifugae Scripturarum:</hi> Night Owls, that do not love the light of that Sun; yea, ſome of your own Church, who are the <hi>pars ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion</hi> thereof (if yet they be of you) have ſaid, <hi>That it is an Herefie to judge of Hereſies, without the Word of God.</hi> So the <hi>Janſeniſts.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And the Reaſon why the generality of <hi>Papiſts,</hi> are ſo deſirous to derline the Scripture, is, becauſe they are conſcious to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, that it is againſt them, as Mr. <hi>White</hi> hath well obſerved <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> of Briſom,
<note place="margin">
                        <p>White<hi>'s way to the Church,</hi> Sect. 7. Numb. 8.</p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Briſtow</hi> Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiv. <hi>ult. Canus</hi> loc. lib. 3. cap. 3.</p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Confil. Epiſc. Bononi Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greg.</hi> Anno 1553. <hi>De ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilienda Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man. Eccleſ.</hi> Fol. 5.</p>
                     </note> who teaching his Scholar, how to deal with a <hi>Proteſtant,</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 words">
                           <desc>〈◊◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> proud Heretick out of his weak and falſe Caſtle of unely Scripturs, into the plain field of Traditions, Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles, Councils, and Fathers; and then, like Cowards, They ſhall not ſtand.</hi> Another <hi>Papiſt</hi> ſaith, <hi>There is more ſtrength is confine Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks in Traditions, than in the Scriptures; yea, all Diſputations with them muſt be determined, by Traditions.</hi> Thoſe Reverend Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers of your Church, that met at <hi>Bononia,</hi> by the <hi>Popes</hi> appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, to conſult of the means for eſtabliſhing of the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> (or healing the Wound of the Daughter of <hi>Babel</hi>) in the counſel they gave to Pope <hi>Julius</hi> the Third, They do confeſs, <hi>Certè vix umbram quandam retinemus in noſtris Eccleſus ejus Doctri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nae, &amp; Diſciplinae quae Apoſtolorum temporibus floruerunt, &amp; prorsùs aliam accerſivimus.</hi> The truth is, we ſearce retain a ſhadow in our Churches of that Doctrine and Diſcipline which flouriſhed in the Apoſtles times, but we have brought in altogether another. <hi>There was no mention,
<note place="margin">Fol. 2.</note> ſay they (for we may confeſs the Truth to your Holineſs, but it muſt he kept cloſe) either of Popes or Cardinals in the Apoſtles times, nor of ſome years after. There were no Monaſteries, nor Priors, nor Abbots, much leſs were there theſe Doctrines, theſe Laws, theſe Cuſtoms, no nor that Empire which now we enjoy over ſeveral peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple and Nations.</hi> They ſay further, <hi>That the not ſtudying the Canon
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:33762:12"/>Law, and Sophiſtry, and Metaphyſicks,</hi> &amp;c.
<note place="margin">Fol 5.</note> 
                     <hi>But learning the Greek and Hebrew Tongues, and examining Tranſlations, by the Greek and Hebrew verity, hath been the cauſe and fountain of the late decay of the Church of</hi> Rome, <hi>and of the deplorable ſtate and condition of her Affairs at this day.</hi> And finally, which they reſerve to the laſt place, as the weightieſt of all their ghoſtly counſels, They adviſe, <hi>That as little as may be of the Goſpel,
<note place="margin">Fol. penult.</note> be read amongſt the people in their vulgar Tongue:</hi> For, <hi>hic ille in ſumma eſt liber, qui praeter caeteros haſce nobis tempeſtates acturbines conciliavit, quibus, prope abrepti ſumus.</hi> For this is in brief, <hi>That Book, which above all others, hath raiſed, and brought upon us theſe ſtorms and whirle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>winds, by which we are almoſt carried away headlong:</hi> Thus ſpeak they. It appears by all this, wherefore it is that you love not the Scripture, even becauſe it reſtifies againſt you: <hi>For he that doth evil, hateth the light; and cometh not to the light, leſt his deeds ſhould be reproved,</hi> John 3.16, 20.</p>
                  <p>As to the word <hi>Hereſie,</hi> for your miſtakes call upon me, to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen it a little; if we look at the notation of it, from <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, <hi>capio, eligo,</hi> ſo it ſignifies any thing of choice, or option, as <hi>Galen,</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, and <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, the Methodical, and the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pirical way of Phyſick; when applyed to matters of Religion, it imports in the largeſt ſignification, any Sect, or way of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion that a man makes choice of, whether true or falſe: So the Sect <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> of the <hi>Sadduces,</hi> Acts 5.17. the Sect of the <hi>Phari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſees,</hi> Acts 15.5. called the moſt exquiſite Sect of our Religion, <hi>Acts</hi> 26.5. the Sect of the <hi>Nazarens,</hi> Acts 24.5. the word is <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, Herefie, in all theſe places. But it is frequently reſtrain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by a <hi>Synecdothe,</hi> to ſignifie a falſe Religion, as ſome other words, ex gr. <hi>Tyrannus magnus,</hi> &amp;c. which are commonly taken <hi>in deteriorem partem:</hi> Thus <hi>Epiphanius</hi> ſeemeth to take it in his Book of Eighty Hereſies, where he numbers <hi>Barbariſm, Seythiſm, Sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iciſm, Platoniſm,</hi> &amp;c. amongſt Hereſies. But it is commonly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained yet more by a further <hi>Synecdoche,</hi> to ſuch Errors as o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verthrow the Foundation, and are obſtinately maintained, againſt Conviction, by perſons pretending (in part) to the True Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; and ſo we do not call <hi>Pagans,</hi> Hereticks, but Infidels. This ſenſe of the word ſeems to be grounded, on 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.10, 11. and 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.1. and <hi>Titus</hi> 3.10, 11. where the Apoſtles do diſtinguiſh of Doctrines, comparing ſome to <hi>Hay and Stubble, yet retaining the true foundation:</hi> But there is another ſort, which
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:33762:13"/>they call, <hi>damnable Hereſies,</hi> or <hi>Hereſies of perdition, Soul-deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Hereſies;</hi> the Aſſertors whereof, are ſubverted, or overturn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, from off the true foundation; and ſelf-condemn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, as ſinning againſt their own light. Now the written Word of God being the onely Rule of True Religion, hence nothing ought to be rejected under the Notion of Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie, but what the Scripture doth condemn as ſuch, <hi>viz.</hi> as falſe, and deſtructive unto Souls, and dangerouſly intrenching upon the very Vitals, and Fundamentals of Religion.</p>
                  <p>And if it be demanded of us, What are the Hereſies of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> in this laſt ſenſe? This is a large Field: <hi>Popery,</hi> ſaith Dr. <hi>Ames,
<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Ames</hi> Caſ. l. 5. c. 4. <hi>de Hae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſ:</hi>
                        </note> Non eſt una aliqua ſingularis Haereſis, ſed quaſi cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pus quoddam ex variis Haereſibus conflatum &amp; productum. Sicut enim</hi> Mahumetiſmus <hi>eſt antecedentium Haereſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>n mixtura, in Oriente &amp; Meridie; ſic</hi> Papiſmus, <hi>quamvis aliâ ſpecie variarum Haereſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>n ſentina eſt in Occidente &amp; Septentrione.</hi> Popery, is not one ſingle Hereſie, but a Sink of many Hereſies, a dead Sea, a Sodomitick Lake of many poyſonous and erroneous Opinions. Look, as <hi>Mahometiſm</hi> is a mixture of former Hereſies, in the Eaſtern and Southern Countries; ſo is <hi>Papiſm</hi> (though under different pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenſions) a Sink of many Hereſies, in the Weſtern and Northern parts of the old <hi>Roman</hi> Empire. Take at preſent, for I would not leave things at random, theſe few Inſtances of the Hereſies your Church hath fallen into. It is eaſie, ſeeing you call us to it; it is eaſie, in the ſtrength of Chriſt, in the evidence of his Word and Spirit, to make good the Charge againſt Her.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. IV. <hi>Of the Hereſies of the Church of</hi> Rome, <hi>eight particulars inſtanced.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THe firſt grand Error of your Church, is this, Your De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throning and Unlording the Scripture. It is Chriſts own phraſe, <hi>Matth.</hi> 15.6. and <hi>Mark</hi> 7.13. by way of Reproof to your Predeceſſors, thoſe ancient <hi>Papiſts,</hi> the <hi>Phariſees,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, Unlording the Word of
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:33762:13"/>God, through your Tradition. But to this written Word, did Jeſus Chriſt appeal, <hi>John</hi> 5.39. <hi>Search the Scriptures, for in them ye think to have eternal life, and they are they which teſtifie of me.</hi> We are commanded, <hi>to try the ſpirits,</hi> 1 John 4.1. even by the Rule laid down in that Scripture, <hi>ver.</hi> 2. The <hi>Bereans</hi> are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended by the Holy Ghoſt, as Chriſtians of the right breed, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, becauſe they would not take the Apoſtles Doctrine upon truſt, but <hi>ſearched the Scriptures daily, whether thoſe things were ſo. Therefore many of them believed,</hi> Acts 17 11, 12. But with you, it is a Noſe of Wax, attramentary Divinity, of no more Authority in it ſelf, than <hi>Aeſop</hi>'s Fables, or <hi>Titus Livius,</hi> but that your Church hath chriſtened it for Scripture; but yet She tells us withall, That we muſt receive Her Traditions, <hi>Pari pietatis affectu, &amp; reverentia,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Concil. Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent. S ſſ.</hi> 4. <hi>Decret.</hi> 1.</note> with as much pious affection and reverence, as we receive the Scripture. So your <hi>Tridentine</hi> Council. It is lamentable to conſider, how many Bibles you have burnt, and how many Chriſtians you have burnt alive, for having Bibles, and labouring to acquaint themſelves therewith. In King <hi>Henry</hi> the Eighth's time, thoſe of you, who then had, the conduct of Affairs in <hi>England,</hi> did cauſe to be put forth a publick and authentick Inſtrument, for the aboliſhing, and inhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biting of the Scriptures, wherein, ye thus expreſs your ſelves,
<note place="margin">Da<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ed. <hi>May</hi> 24. 1531.</note> 
                  <hi>That foraſ much as there is ingendered an Opinion in divers of his Subjects, that it is his Graces duty to cauſe the Scripture of God to be Tranſlated into the Engliſh Tongue, to be communicated unto the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple.—It appeareth, That the having of the whole Scripture in En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh, is not neceſſary to chriſten men,
<note place="margin">Fox, <hi>Acts and Mon.</hi> Vor. 2. E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>it. 1641.</note> the divulging of the Scripture at this time in the Engliſh Tongue to be committed to the people, conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring ſuch peſtilent Books, and ſo evil Opinions, as be now ſpread among them, ſhould rather be to their further confuſion and deſtruction, than to the edification of their Souls.</hi> Thus you ſaid, and did your worſt, but you could not hinder the Sun from riſing, at its ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed hour; nor fruſtrate the Oath of him, <hi>who ſware, that (your) time ſhould be no longer,</hi> and he gave the book to his ſervants <hi>to propheſie again,</hi> Rev. 10. ver. 6, 9, 11.</p>
               <p>This wretched neglect, and contempt of the Scripture, is the <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, the very corner ſtone of the Tower of <hi>Babel.</hi> We look upon it as the firſt and chief of all your Hereſies, and the ſource and fountain of all the reſt: <hi>Ye do erre, not knowing the Scripture,</hi> Matt. 22.29. For there is a ſelf-evidencing light and
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:33762:14"/>majeſty in the Scripture, it bears the ſtamp and impreſs of the Divine Attributes upon it; which he that ſees not, muſt needs be blind, as to other Truths alſo: As he that cannot ſee the Sun, when it ſhines at Noon-day, can ſee nothing elſe; he that cannot hear the voyce of Thunder, is not like to be awakened, by a ſilent whiſper.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The Authority, and Infallibility of your Church and Pope, as if they were not men, but gods; for, <hi>humanum eſt errare: Let God be true, and every man a lyar,</hi> Rom. 3.4. This is the great Idol that you ſet up againſt the Scripture, and conſequently a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt God himſelf; for the Scripture is God ſpeaking to Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind: Hence it is written of <hi>Antichriſt, that he exalteth himſelf, above all that is called God, or that is worſhipped; ſo that he as God, ſitteth in the temple of God, ſhewing himſelf that he is God,</hi> 2 Theff. 2.4. He takes upon him to diſpenſe even with the Laws of God; therefore it is made the brand of a Reprobate, to worſhip the Beaſt, <hi>Revel.</hi> 13.8. And the Lord denounces and thunders forth damnation to them, <hi>Reve</hi> 14.9, 10, 11. <hi>The ſmoke of their torment aſcendeth up for ever and ever;</hi> and their doom is juſt, for they make a god of him; for, put caſe the Pope ſhould erre, and go to Hell,
<note place="margin">Bell. <hi>De ſummo Pontif.</hi> lib. 4. cap. 5.</note> 
                  <hi>Bellarmine</hi> would fain make us believe, that we are bound in conſcience to go with him, for thus he ſpeaketh: <hi>Si Papa ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raret praecipiendo vitia vel prohibendo virtutes, teneretur Eccleſia credere vitia eſſe bona &amp; virtutes malas, niſi vellet contra conſcientiam peccare.</hi> If the Pope ſhould erre in commanding Vices, and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidding Vertues, the Church were bound to believe that Vice is good, and that Virtue is evil, unleſs ſhe would fin againſt her Conſcience. Here is ſweet Catholick Doctrine, is it not? yet ſuch ſtuffe as this, is of ſuch value, with you, that the ſame <hi>Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larmine</hi> ſaith,
<note place="margin">Bell. <hi>Praefat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in li<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>res <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>e Fortif.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Quâ de re agitur, cum de primatu Pontificis agitur? breviſſime dicam, de ſumma rei Chriſtianae;</hi> The Primacy of the Pope, <hi>ſayes he,</hi> is the ſum of Chriſtian Religion, he means Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſtian.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Your arrogant Attributions, to corrupted Free-will, in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogation to the ſovereignty and efficacy of converting and elect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Grace, yea, to the utter corrupting and undermining of ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry great Goſpel-truths, as Election, Regeneration, Aſſurance, Perſeverance; your Free-will, is an Error that draws a ſoul tail after it: But the Scripture ſaith, <hi>We are not born again of the will of man, but of his own will he begat us,</hi> John 1.13. James 1.18.
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:33762:14"/>
                  <hi>So then, it is not of him that willeth, nor of him that runneth;</hi> it is neither Free will, nor good Works, <hi>but it is of God that ſheweth mercy,</hi> Rom. 9.16. <hi>When thou waſt in thy blood, yea, when thou waſt in thy blood, I ſaid unto thee, Live,</hi> Ezek. 16.6. Which is that that fills the hearts of his people, with ſuch admiring and ado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring thoughts of the freedom, and ſovereignty, and efficacy of his grace. That <hi>gratia vorti-cordia,</hi> as <hi>Auſtin</hi> ſpeaks, that won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derful <hi>heart-changing grace,</hi> that ſlayes the enmity, ſubdues the heart, and turns the will; <hi>who was before a blaſphemer, and a perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, and injurious, but I obtained mercy.—Now to the King eternal, immortal, inviſible, the onely wiſe God, be honour and glory, for ever and ever, Amen,</hi> 1 Tim. 1.13, 14, 15, 16, 17. <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nto him that hath loved us, and waſhed us from our ſins, with his own blood, and hath made us Kings and Prieſts unto God, and his Father, to him be glory and dominion, for ever and ever, Amen,</hi> Revel. 1.5.6. But he that thinks he is converted, and doth not ſing his Hallelujahs and Songs of ſalvation, for it, to this King Eternal, Immortal, Inviſible, and to the Lamb that was ſlain, and to the power of his Spirit, but to his own corrupted will: As he ſets the Crown upon his own head, and robs God of his glory, as if he were not Maſter, and ſovereign diſpoſer of his own gifts and graces, ſo he doth thereby give in evidence againſt himſelf, that he ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver knew the grace of God in truth; The whole work of our ſalvation is both begun and carried on, by free grace alone, from firſt to laſt; from the foundation thereof, in election to the top<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone of glorification, the Saints <hi>cry grace, grace unto it,</hi> Zach. 4.7. <hi>That as ſin hath reigned unto death, even ſo grace might reign through righteouſneſs unto eternal life by Jeſus Chriſt our Lord,</hi> Rom. 5. ult.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Your Juſtification by the merit of good Works, to the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite diſhonour of the grace and blood of Chriſt, and to the keeping of afflicted Conſciences upon the rack of everlaſting perplexity and trouble: for Conſcience once effectually awake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, will never be pacified, but by the blood of Chriſt, for <hi>we are juſtified freely by his grace, through the redemption that is in Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> Rom. 3.24. <hi>When you have done all thoſe things that are commanded you, ſay we are but unprofitable ſervants,</hi> and where then is merit? <hi>Luke</hi> 17.7, 8, 9, 10. There is iniquity even in our holy things, <hi>Exod.</hi> 28.38. Our beſt Duties are in part defiled, and mixed with ſin. The very tears of Repentance need waſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:33762:15"/>with the blood of Chriſt. Therefore well did <hi>Auſtin</hi> pray, <hi>Lava Lachrymas meas Domine.</hi> You can allow the righteouſneſs of a meer man, or of a woman, of a Monk, or a Nun, to be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted and reckoned to another, as in your Supererogations, and yet cavil at the imputation of Chriſts righteouſneſs.</p>
               <p>This is a Truth of ſo great weight, that <hi>Luther</hi> called it, <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulus ſtantis aut cadentis Eccleſiae,</hi> the very Criſis and chief Indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of the Churches ſtate, ſhe ſtands or falls with this Truth. And as the Scripture deſcribes the Proteſtant Reformation by their ſtanding upon the Sea of glaſs, as ſpiritual Prieſts, waſhing themſelves in the Righteouſneſs of Chriſt, and making their Robes white with the blood of the Lamb, whereof the molten Sea and Lavers of the Temple were a Type, <hi>Revel.</hi> 4.6. and 7.14. and 15.2. So indeed it was upon this grand Truth, and Principle of the Goſpel,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Dr.</hi> Grew <hi>of Justification.</hi> Preface.</note> as Dr. <hi>Grew</hi> hath well obſerved, That <hi>Luther,</hi> that Champion of the Lord, did pitch the Field againſt you: And well he might, for the Apoſtle doubteth not to tell the <hi>Galathians</hi> when corrupted here, That <hi>Chriſt was become of none effect to them,</hi> and <hi>that they were fullen from grace, and turned to another Goſpel,</hi> Galat. 5.4. <hi>and</hi> 1.6. Our Juſtification by the blood of Chriſt, and our Regeneration by his Spirit, being the two main parts of thoſe glad tydings of the Goſpel, by which it refreſhes and gives reſt to weary Souls. And therefore to deny theſe, or to aſcribe them to other cauſes, as to our own Wills or Works, as it is to ſend diſtreſſed Souls to the Brooks of <hi>Teman</hi> in a day of drought, and unto Waters that fail; ſo it is to reject at once, both the Blood of the Covenant, and alſo the Spirit of the Covenant of Grace, and ſo to turn both Jeſus Chriſt, and the Holy Ghoſt, as it were, out of Office: For, it is a Truth as firm as the foundations of the Earth, and as immoveable as the Pillars of Heaven, that it is the peculiar work and glory, both of the blood of Chriſt, to juſtifie and reconcile, and of his Spirit to convert, and apply that precious blood: And ſeeing the riches of his Free-grace appears, and ſhines forth exceeding gloriouſly, in theſe influences of his blood and Spirit into our ſalvation; therefore to detract from theſe, by founding it in our own Wills or Works, is to eclipſe the glory of his Grace. From all which, you may ſee the danger of both theſe Errors of your Church, there being nothing wherein the enmity of corrupt Nature a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Goſpel, doth more directly work out and vent it ſelf,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:33762:15"/>like the venom of Aſps, and as the poyſon of Dragons, then in theſe deluſions, of Converſion by your own Wills, and Juſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation by your own Works.</p>
               <p n="5">5. A fifth pernicious Error of the <hi>Roman</hi> Church, is Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, and Superſtition of all ſorts, contrary to the very Letter of the Second Commandment: As worſhipping Images, praying to Saints and Angels, your Cake-Idol, or Breaden-god; Your Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criledge of the Cup in the Lords Supper; Your five ſupernu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merary Sacraments; Your Latin-Service; Your Superſtitious, or Religious Orders, as you call them; Your prohibition of of Meats and Marriage; Your Holy Water, Reliques, Pilgrima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> As it were on every high Hill, and under every green Tree, hath that Idolatrous Church play'd the Harlot; whereby ſhe ſcandaliſeth and hardeneth both <hi>Jews</hi> and <hi>Turks</hi> againſt the Goſpel: Yea, ſhe hath corrupted and intoxicated almoſt all the Churches in the world, with this ſin, and made all Nations <hi>drunk with the wine of the wrath of her Fornication,</hi> for which the Holy Ghoſt brands her, as <hi>THE MOTHER OF HARLOTS,</hi> Revel. 17.5. and 18.3. Yea, though ſhe hath ſeen the jealou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie, and the fury of her Husband, againſt her treacherous ſiſter <hi>Judah, yet ſhe feareth not.</hi> I mean, the deſolations of the Eaſtern Churches, by thoſe Inſtruments of his fury, thoſe Angels of his wrath, whom the Lord hath let looſe upon them, from about the River <hi>Euphrates;</hi> the <hi>Turks,</hi> who have deſtroyed and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jugated a third part of the Chriſtian world for this ſin, yet ſhe repenteth not, being beſotted, and dead drunk with the poyſon of her own Fornications, and given up to a reprobate ſenſe; ſhe hath a heart that cannot repent of ſuch a Church-deſtroying, ſuch a God-provoking ſin, as was propheſied of her in the ſixth Trumpet, <hi>Revel.</hi> 9.13.—20. The Learned <hi>Raynolds</hi> hath ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken very convictingly to you, concerning this ſin, in his Book, <hi>De Idololatria Romanae Eccleſiae:</hi> And ſo hath <hi>Mede,</hi> of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaſie of the latter Times.</p>
               <p n="6">6. All your ſeditious Principles againſt Kings and Magiſtrates, exempting your Clergy, exalting your Pope above them. The number of thoſe you thus exempt, as ſous of <hi>Belial</hi> from the yoke, hath been eſtimated to amount in ſpacious Popiſh Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries, to a very great proportion, even to an Hundred thouſand able fighting Men in one Nation; which brings to mind that ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion of your own Pope <hi>Gregory, That Antichriſt hath an Army
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:33762:16"/>of Prieſts to fight his Battels.</hi> Rex ſuperbiae prope eſt, &amp; quod dici<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>neſas eſt,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Greg.</hi> Lib. 4. Epiſt. 38.</note> Sacerdotum praeparatus eſt exercitus qui cervici militant elatioms, &amp;c. <hi>The King of pride</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>is at the door, and which is dreadful to be ſpoken, there is an Army of Prieſts ready to fight under that neck of pride which lifteth up it ſelf,</hi> &amp;c. The fifth Trumpet proclaimeth, that he hath a black Guard of Scorpion-locuſts, who know no other King but him whom the Holy Ghoſt hath named according to his Nature, <hi>Abaddon, and Apollyon,</hi> the great Deſtroyer, the Son of Perdition, the Man of Sin, <hi>Revel.</hi> 9. <hi>ver.</hi> 3, 11. And as you thus rob and ſpoil Kings of their Subjects, ſo you make Kings themſelves Subjects to the Pope, exalting his Throne with <hi>Lucifer, above the ſtars of God, Iſa.</hi> 14.13. And giving him ſuch a barbarous power over them, that it is a wonderful and unaccountable thing that ever any King or Magiſtrate ſhould be a Papiſt; no account can be given of it, but the ſtrange corruption of Nature, neither their Crowns, nor Lives, being ſecure, but meerly at the Popes cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſie, upon the principles of that Religion, which gives a forreign Prieſt power to depoſe them, and give away their King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms.</p>
               <p>But the Apoſtle <hi>Peter,</hi> a great Apoſtle, and whom you pretend a kindneſs, and a reſpect for, he exhorts us to <hi>ſubmit to every Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance of man for the Lords ſake; to the King as ſupreme,</hi> 1 Pet. 2.13. But not a word of the Popes Supremacy. And the Apoſtle <hi>Paul,</hi> though an Apoſtle, yet did appeal unto <hi>Caeſar,</hi> as knowing that to be the ſupreme Tribunal on earth in ſubordination un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God, for God alone is chief, and the Magiſtrates power ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinate unto Gods, <hi>Acts</hi> 25.10, 11. &amp; 5.29. And he exhort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth <hi>every ſoul,</hi> which includeth the Pope, if he hath an humane ſoul, <hi>to be ſubject to the higher powers,</hi> Rom. 13. ver. 1. to 7. There may be paſſive obedience when men cannot act, therefore we whom you call Hereticks, have ſet it down as amongſt the Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles of our Faith, that Infidelity, or difference in Religion, doth not make void the Magiſtrates juſt and legal Authority, nor free the people from their obedience to him, from which Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal perſons are not exempted, much leſs hath the Pope any pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, or Juriſdiction over them in their Dominions, or over any of their people, and leaſt of all to deprive them of their Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions or Lives, if he ſhall judge them to be Hereticks, or upon any other pretence whatſoever; yea, ſome of your own have
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:33762:16"/>confeſſed, That from the beginning it was not ſo.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                        </gap> Julio.</hi> 3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> 2. B.</note> 
                  <hi>Quin omnes emnium Eccleſiarum Miniſtri, Romanae non minus quam caeterarum ultro Regibus Principibus ac Magiſtratibus parebant.</hi> But all the Miniſters of all the Churches, yea, of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> as well as any other, were willingly obedient unto Kings, Princes, and Magiſtrates. So thoſe <hi>Bononian</hi> Fathers of yours before mentioned. How, and by what means,
<note place="margin">Morney <hi>Myst. Iniq. per totum:</hi> Fox <hi>Acts and Monum.</hi> Vol. 1. pa. 1018.</note> and by what ſteps and degrees, the Pope roſe from ſuch mean beginnings, to ſuch an height of worldly power and grandeur, to tread upon the Necks of Kings and Princes, <hi>Guiccardin</hi> hath fully ſhewed in his digreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, towards the end of the fourth Book of his Hiſtories, which you have honeſtly ſtollen away out of ſome Editions, but in ſome others it is reſtored. <hi>Morney</hi> alſo ſpeaks fully to it, as being a great part of his ſcope, and ſo doth Mr. <hi>Fox.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="7">7. Your ſanguinary Spirit and Principles, towards ſuch as differ from, and teſtifie againſt you: Wherein there is not only an evil in practice, but your practice being juſtified as lawful by your principle, it is two ſins conjoyned, it is both Murther and Hereſie, and moſt remote from the Spirit of the Goſpel, which is a Spirit of love and ſweetneſs; yea, it is a principal character of Antiohriſt, and mark of the Beaſt, <hi>Revel.</hi> 13.7. <hi>and</hi> 17.6. The <hi>Revelation</hi> often mentions theſe two ſins, the Sorceries and For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nications of your falſe Worſhip, and your ſhedding innocent and precious blood, as the two grand procuring cauſes of your Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ine: See <hi>Revel.</hi> 18.2. <hi>ult.</hi> and <hi>Revel.</hi> 19.2.</p>
               <p>It is <hi>Ramus</hi> his Obſervation, that great Light, and faithful Martyr of Jeſus Chriſt, whom you ſlew, with Thirty thouſand more, in your great <hi>Pariſian</hi> Maſſacre in the year 1572.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>P: Rami</hi> Commentar. de Religione Chriſtiana. <hi>Lib.</hi> 4. <hi>cap.</hi> 19. <hi>pag.</hi> 546.</note> It is his Obſervation and Lamentation, How that <hi>Julian</hi> the Apoſtate could obſerve, and teſtifie concerning the Chriſtian Religion, in thoſe primitive times, That it came to be ſo largely diffuſed and propagated, by means of the good turns and offices of love, which Chriſtians did towards all men of what Religion, or per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuaſion ſoever: But we, in theſe dayes (we <hi>Romaniſts</hi>) are of ſuch a ſpirit, that if our Neighbour do not conſent, and concur, and run along with us in every ſuperſtitious practice and opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, we preſently burn him alive. <hi>Julianus Apoſtata ad Arſacium Cappadociae Pontificem ſcripſit, Chriſtianam Religionem tam late propagatam eſſe propter Chriſtianorum erga omnet cujuſvis Religionis mortales beneficentiam. Nos vero, niſi de cujuſſibet ſuperſtitionis opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nione
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:33762:17"/>proximus noſter conſentiat, igne vivum protinus exurimus.</hi> You have ſlain (as ſome compute) a greater number of Chriſtians fince the firſt ſetting up of your Inquiſition, than there be Papiſts at this day in the World.
<q>
                     <l>— Quis talia fando</l>
                     <l>Temperet à Lachrymis?</l>
                  </q> Who that hath either the grace of a Chriſtian, or but the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon bowels of a man, can ſpeak of ſuch things, without bleed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Lamentations! <hi>Alſtedins</hi> obſerves, <hi>That in the ſpace of Forty years,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Alſted</hi> Ency<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clop. Chronol. <hi>cap.</hi> 8. <hi>ad An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num</hi> 1540.</note> from the year</hi> 1540, <hi>there were Nine hundred thouſand Martyrs in</hi> Europe. Should we Travel into Forreign Affairs, and former Ages, I might tell you of your bloody Croiſadoes againſt <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians,</hi> inſtead of <hi>Turks,</hi> againſt the <hi>Waldenſes,</hi> and <hi>Abbingenſes</hi> of old, as well of late, your Spaniſh Inquiſitions, to which King <hi>Philip</hi> the ſecond, delivered up his own eldeſt Son and Heir <hi>Charles,</hi> to be butchered and murthered by them, for ſuſpition of ſavouring the <hi>Low-Countrey</hi> Hereticks. Your <hi>French</hi> Maſſacres, and <hi>Thyeſtaean</hi> Feaſts and Nuptials, at which you have drank more Blood, than Wine! The barbarous <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Butcheries in the <hi>Netherlands:</hi> And with how much blood your <hi>Romiſh</hi> Faith was planted in the <hi>Weſt-Indies,</hi> to the infinite ſcandal and diſhonour of the Name of Chriſt, even in the blood of Nineteen Millions of poor innocent Natives, as <hi>Acoſta,</hi> the Jeſuite, a Bird of your Neſt, as ſome have Noted, Relates the ſtory. But to come nearer home, there were near about Three hundred ſlain, and burnt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>live in <hi>England,</hi> in Queen <hi>Maries</hi> time: And in the late Maſſacre and Rebellion here in <hi>Ireland,</hi> there were about Three hundred thouſand <hi>Engliſh Proteſtants</hi> murthered by you, whereof above one half, above One hundred and fifty thouſand in the firſt ſix Months of that Rebellion, moſt perfidiouſly and treacherouſly, in a time of Peace, without ever declaring War, and without a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny provocation given.</p>
               <p>Theſe be ſome of the Hereſies, and falſe Doctrines of your Church;
<note place="margin">Rev. 17.3.5.</note> ſome of the Blaſphemies written in the Forehead of Myſtical <hi>Babylon,</hi> which ſhe owneth and maintaineth in an open and avowed manner.</p>
               <p n="8">8. But I have not here mentioned her conſequential Errors, becauſe they are innumerable. For thus, there is no ſound part
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:33762:17"/>in her, but from the ſole of the foot, even to the crown of the head, there is nothing but wounds, and bruiſes, and putrifying ſores. Thus, ſhe is at defiance even with common ſenſe and rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon; ſhe will not believe the report of three ſenſes, in the buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the carnal preſence: For as the Apoſtle calls it, <hi>This bread, this bread, this bread,</hi> three times after the Conſecration, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.26, 27, 28. So the eye ſaith it is bread, the taſte, the touch ſay the ſame, ſhe ſees it, feels it, and taſtes it; but yet ſhe believes there is no bread there, which is to lay aſide the uſe of reaſon, and to turn Sott and Sceptick. The madneſs of which deluſion, did ſo ſcandalize <hi>Averroes,</hi> the <hi>Arabian</hi> Philoſopher, that when they asked him upon his Death-bed, <hi>What Religion he dyed in?</hi> He gave this Anſwer, <hi>Quia Chriſtiani manducant Deum ſuum, &amp; adorant quod comedunt, ſit anima mea cum Philoſophis:</hi> Becauſe the Chriſtians eat their God with their teeth, and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip that which they eat, let my ſoul be with the Philoſophers. But having heard of the glorious Name and Fame of Chriſt, and Chriſtianity, it had been his Duty, and would have been his Happineſs, to have made a thorow ſearch into the Fountain of that Religion, which is the Scriptures of Truth; and there he might have found, that this abominable Idolatry, is no part at all of the Chriſtian Religion, but of the Antichriſtian Apoſtaſie, of the Mother of Harlots; yea, there is hardly any Article of the Chriſtian Faith, which ſhe doth not ſome way or other, by evident and unavoidable conſequence, corrupt and ſubvert: As for inſtance, ſhe denies by conſequence that Chriſt is come in the fleſh, which is one of the Characters of Antichriſt, 1 <hi>John</hi> 4.3. She denies the Reality of the Humane Nature of Chriſt, by her Tranſubſtantiation; for ſhe leaves him only a Phantaſtick, or Imaginary body, having not the true Nature, and dimenſions of a body; yea, ſhe doth impugn and ſubvert, by true and ſound conſequence of Reaſon, that great Fundamental, of One God: As was ingeniouſly made out, by an Engliſh Gentleman, a <hi>Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant,</hi> in diſcourſe with a <hi>Roman Catholick,</hi> thus; <hi>That is not the true Religion, that doth not acknowledge One God, but Popery doth not acknowledge One God: For did you not pray to the Virgin</hi> Mary <hi>this morning?</hi> The <hi>Roman Catholick</hi> replyed, <hi>Yes:</hi> To which the <hi>Proteſtant</hi> made this Return, <hi>And did not Five thouſand pray to her at the ſame time?</hi> The <hi>Papiſt</hi> anſwered, <hi>Yes, doubtleſs.</hi> From whence the <hi>Proteſtant</hi> inferred, <hi>Then either you prayed like a Fool,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:33762:18"/>or elſe ſhe heard you all, and knows all your hearts; but this is to make her a God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Theſe therefore, are ſome of the <hi>Roman</hi> Hereſies; <hi>Her dethro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the Scripture; The Popes Infallibility; Converſion by Free-will; Juſtification by Works; Idolatry and Superſtition; Her ſeditious Principles; Her ſanguinary Principles; Her conſequential Errors:</hi> Yet this is but a general and brief induction of them.</p>
               <p>But now do you ask, Who ever teſtified againſt her? <hi>Proh pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dorem tuum!</hi> Although if no man had, yet that is no ſufficient evidence of her Innocency; the cauſe doth not depend upon this: But yet withall you know, if you know any thing of the Hiſtories of the Church, in former times, That the Errors and Corruptions of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> have been teſtified againſt, all along by faithful men, whom God hath raiſed up from Age to Age, to be the Witneſſes of his Truth; for the Lord gave his two Witneſſes light, and grace, and power, to propheſie in ſackcloth 1260 dayes, <hi>Revel.</hi> 11.3. There was a Woman in the Wilderneſs, when Antichriſt was upon the Throne, <hi>Revel.</hi> 12.14. There were Saints, whom the Beaſt did perſecute and war a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt, during all the time of his Reign, <hi>Revel.</hi> 13.7. Would you know their names <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> you may ſee ſome of them, in divers of our Divines, and Writers, who have taken the pains to preſent you with Inſtances and Catalogues of ſome of the chief, and moſt eminent. And common Reaſon will eaſily ſuggeſt unto you, That if there were ſo many left upon Record, there muſt needs be many more, whoſe names, the Hiſtories of former times have not preſerved, and delivered down to poſterity: But you may ſee a competent number of Witneſſes againſt you, in the Centu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſts of <hi>Magdeburg</hi> in <hi>Flacius Illyricus</hi> his <hi>Catalogus teſtium verita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis: Morney</hi> his Hiſtory of the Papacy, or Myſtery of Iniquity. <hi>Fox</hi> his Book of <hi>Martyrs. Raynolds</hi> his Conference with <hi>Hart.</hi> Sundry of our Expoſitors on the <hi>Revelation.</hi> See Mr. <hi>Arthur Dent</hi> on <hi>Chap.</hi> 11. <hi>White</hi>'s way to the Church. <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſher</hi> againſt <hi>Maloone:</hi> And of the Religion anciently profeſſed by the <hi>Iriſh,</hi> and <hi>Britiſh,</hi> and <hi>de ſtatu &amp; ſucceſſione Eccleſ. Brittanicarum:</hi> Yea, your own <hi>Bellarmine</hi> giveth ſome account of thoſe that have even from the primitive times, oppoſed and impugned the Primacy of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> though he doth it briefly, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectively enough; for he omits, beſides other things, all the <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frican</hi> Biſhops and Councils, <hi>Bell: Praefat. in libros de Pontif.</hi> This
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:33762:18"/>may ſuffice at preſent, as to the Errors and Hereſies of your Church. Your next endeavour, is to defend her, from the charge of Schiſm: Let us proceed, in the ſtrength and grace of Chriſt, to conſider that alſo.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. V. <hi>Of the Nature of Schiſm, and of the Schiſms of the Church of</hi> Rome, <hi>both within her ſelf, and from other Churches.</hi>
               </head>
               <div type="discourse">
                  <head>DISCOURSE.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>SChiſm is a departure or diviſion from the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity of the Church, whereby the band and communion held with ſome former Church, is broken and diſſolved. If ever the Church of</hi> Rome <hi>divided Her ſelf by Schiſm, from any other body of faithful Chriſtians, or broke communion, or went forth from the ſoci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ety of any elder Church, I pray ſatisfie your ſelf and me in theſe par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars. Firſt, Whoſe company did ſhe leave? Secondly, From what body did ſhe go forth? Where was the true Church which ſhe forſook?</hi> And the ſame thing is repeated again, a ſecond and a third time in your Paper.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="answer">
                  <head>ANSWER.</head>
                  <p>You do here again, as before, in your deſcription of <hi>Apoſtaſie</hi> and <hi>Hereſie,</hi> deſcribe the thing amiſs, that you may the better ward off the blow, and de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="4 letters">
                        <desc>••••</desc>
                     </gap> your Church; Not that we de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to ſtrive with you about words, but as they do involve erro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neous, and undue apprehenſions of things: Be it granted, That <hi>Schiſm</hi> is a rent, or a breach of that Unity that Chriſt hath ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed in his Church; and ſo as <hi>Hereſie</hi> denies the Faith, <hi>Schiſm</hi> deſtroyes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> of the Goſpel; but your deſcripti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of it fails in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</p>
                  <pb n="30" facs="tcp:33762:19"/>
                  <p n="1">I. There may be <hi>Schiſm</hi> in a Church within it ſelf: The Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle ſeveral times uſeth this word, in this <hi>Epiſtle</hi> to the <hi>Corinthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi> as 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.10. and <hi>cap.</hi> 11.18. and <hi>cap.</hi> 12.25. <hi>I hear,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>that, when you come together in the Church, there be <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, diviſions, or ſchiſms among you:</hi> Though that any of them did break off from the communion of the Church, doth not appear; but there were carnal contendings and ſtrivings within, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong themſelves, rending and tearing one another, which the Apoſtle there calls Rents or Schiſms.</p>
                  <p n="2">II. There may be <hi>Schiſm</hi> from another Church, contempora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry and coexiſtent, as well as from a Church praeexiſtent. There is no neceſſity, that it muſt be only from a former Elder Church; yea, an Elder Church may be guilty of <hi>Schiſm</hi> from a younger, and from thoſe that were her own Members, if ſhe break the bond of love and order with them, by her own corruptions, and perſecutions. It is the apoſtatizing, perſecuting Church, that makes the rent, and is guilty of the <hi>Schiſm,</hi> and not the Reform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing party, who are driven out by them.</p>
                  <p>Now to apply theſe things a little to the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> ſhe may be charged with <hi>Schiſm</hi> upon all theſe Accounts: The plain truth is, ſhe is the moſt <hi>Schiſmatical</hi> Church in the World, both within her ſelf, and in reference to other Churches alſo a the evidence whereof is ſo notorious, that if I were a <hi>Roman Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick,</hi> I would tell you, That it was very unhappily, and unad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſedly done of you, to mention this buſineſs of <hi>Schiſm,</hi> in a Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per of Diſpute offered by you to the Hereticks.</p>
                  <p>For firſt, within her ſelf. Her inteſtine Schiſms and Diviſions have been ſo many, that it would make this Paper ſwell into a Volume,
<note place="margin">Bell: <hi>Praef. in Libr. de Pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tif.</hi>
                     </note> to number them all up unto you. It is <hi>Bellarmines</hi> own conceſſion, though he labours alſo to cover this nakedneſs with a Fig leaf, That there were <hi>Schiſmata graviſſima &amp; plurima ipſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum interaſe Romanorum Pontificum.</hi> Very grievous, and very many Schiſms,
<note place="margin">Voet. <hi>Diſp. Vol.</hi> 2. <hi>Diſ.</hi> 43. p.</note> even of the Popes of <hi>Rome</hi> amongſt themſelves. <hi>Voetius</hi> refers you to <hi>Mayer</hi>'s Book, of the Six and twenty Schiſms of the Church and See of <hi>Rome;</hi>
                     <note place="margin">689. Onuphr. <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man. Pontif. &amp; Cardinal. ad Annum Chriſti</hi> 1378.</note> but your own <hi>Onuphrius</hi> reckons up no leſs than Twenty nine Schiſms in the Church of <hi>Rome:</hi> And of the Twenty eighth in the time of <hi>Clement</hi> the ſeventh, he ſaith, it was <hi>Peſſimum &amp; diuturnum Schiſma, omniſque Res-publica Chriſtiana diviſa.</hi> A moſt wicked and long laſting Schiſm; for it laſted, as he ſaith, no leſs than One and fifty
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:33762:19"/>years together, and the whole Chriſtian world was divided by it; the <hi>French, Spaniards,</hi> and others, following <hi>Clement</hi> the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venth; but <hi>Germany, Hungary, England,</hi> and part of <hi>Italy,</hi> fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed <hi>Urban</hi> the ſixth. Moreover,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Anno Chriſti circiter</hi> 897. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                     </note> to mention another inſtance among ſo many, the Schiſms were ſo violent between Pope <hi>Ste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phanus,</hi> and Pope <hi>Formoſus,</hi> and their Succeſſors, That they did nothing but do, and undo; Ratifie, and Reſcind the Acts and Decrees of one another. <hi>Stephanus,</hi> for his part, he Reſcinds the Decrees of <hi>Formoſus,</hi> and like a quiet, and peaceable man, digs him up out of his Grave, cuts off his Fingers, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> But Pope <hi>Romanus,</hi> and <hi>Theodorus,</hi> and <hi>John</hi> the Tenth, diſannulled the Acts of <hi>Stephen,</hi> and approved <hi>Formoſus:</hi> Yet after theſe, comes <hi>Sergius</hi> the third, who digs up <hi>Formoſus</hi> his dead body once more, cuts off his Head, caſts it into <hi>Tyber,</hi> Reſcinds his Decrees. Now the Queſtion is, Which of them ſhall we believe? for,
<note place="margin">Bell. <hi>de Pontif. lib</hi> 4. <hi>cap.</hi> 12.</note> they were all infallible. <hi>Bellarmine</hi> determines, That <hi>Stephanus</hi> and <hi>Sergius</hi> were in the Error, and ſo like an Heretick he takes upon him to judge the Pope: And as you have Popes and Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>popes, ſo you have Councils againſt Councils; for inſtance,
<note place="margin">V. Calviſ. <hi>Chr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>
                           <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nol. ad annum:</hi> 1437.</note> your Councils of <hi>Conſtanoe</hi> and <hi>Baſil</hi> have defined, That the Council is above the Pope. <hi>Quod niſi eſt, quis unquam Romano Pontifici quamvis improbiſſimo contradicerei?</hi> Which if it be not ſo, Who would ever gainſay the Pope, though never ſo wicked, ſay they of <hi>Baſil</hi> in their Bull, <hi>Jan.</hi> 17. 1438. But Pope <hi>Leo,</hi> and the Council of <hi>Lateran,</hi> have determined the contrary. And here again,
<note place="margin">Bell. <hi>de Conci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liorum autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritate.</hi> lib. 2. cap. 19. <hi>&amp; de Eceleſ. mili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tante.</hi> lib. 3. cap. 16.</note> 
                     <hi>Bellarmine</hi> takes upon him to determine between the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenting Popes and Councils, and plonounceth that of <hi>Baſil,</hi> as ſoon as Antichriſt was angry with them, to be but <hi>Conciliabulum, &amp;c.</hi> But, in the mean time, your boaſtings of a Supreme, Infal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lible, Viſible Judge amongſt you, to end your Controverſies, are to much purpoſe, unleſs <hi>Bellarmine</hi> be he; but he is dead, and who ſucceeds him in the Office, I cannot tell. And, I wonder, What became of your uninterrupted Succeſſion all this while, during all theſe Broyles and Schiſms? And where is your P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> and Unity among your ſelves? When <hi>Bellarmine</hi> almoſt upon every Controverſie, reports the contrary Opinions of your own Doctors, ſome of which he condemns very ſeverely.
<note place="margin">Voet. <hi>Diſp. part.</hi> 2 <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventar. Eccleſ. Roman.</hi> p. 689.</note> I have not told them how many they be, but <hi>Voetius</hi> ſaith, He mentions no leſs than Two hundred contrary Opinions amongſt your own Writers, which your Infallible Judge (as it ſeemeth) hath not
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:33762:20"/>determined to this day. I might here mention, as ſignal Inſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces thereof, The ſharp Conteſts, and Digladiations between your <hi>Dominicans</hi> and <hi>Franciſcans,</hi> and <hi>Jeſuites,</hi> about the power and intereſts of Free-will, and Free-grace, and the influence there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of into mans Converſion and Predeſtination; and about the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maculate Conception of the bleſſed Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> about which your <hi>Trent</hi> Council durſt not give a clear definitive ſentence, but ſpeaks ambiguouſly, like the Delphick Oracles of old: As alſo the Conteſts between your <hi>French Sorboniſts,</hi> and your <hi>Hildebran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dine Paraſites</hi> of the Court of <hi>Rome,</hi> about the pragmatick Sanction of the Council of <hi>Baſil,</hi> the Liberties of the <hi>Gallican</hi> Church, the power of Popes, in reference to Councils and Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Nor, indeed, do I know any one point, wherein you differ from the <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> wherein you are agreed amongſt your ſelves: Your very Council of <hi>Trent,</hi> though approved by the Pope, yet is rejected by the <hi>French Papiſts</hi> unto this day. This is your peace and unity amongſt your ſelves, whereof you uſe to boaſt ſo much; Nothing, forſooth, but Mufick and Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony, made up of Diſcords.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, As to other Churches. There be Churches both elder and younger, and contemporary with the <hi>Roman,</hi> and ſome of her own ſounder Members, with all which ſhe hath broke com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion; And they are not <hi>fugitivi,</hi> but <hi>fugati;</hi> it is not they, but ſhe that hath made the breach, becauſe ſhe doth impoſe ſuch conditions of communion upon them, as they cannot lawfully ſubmit unto; <hi>viz.</hi> To receive all her Errors, and ſubmit their Conſciences to her, and her Head as Infallible and Supreme.</p>
                  <p>If we look back to the firſt times of your Apoſtaſie, there were firſt, all the Churches and Chriſtians, without the bounds of the <hi>Roman</hi> Empire, as in <hi>India, Perfia,</hi> &amp;c. Secondly, the <hi>Grecian</hi> Churches, which were one half of that Empire, one Leg of <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niels</hi> Image, <hi>Dan.</hi> 2. which took the Alarum very early, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed the primacy of <hi>Rome,</hi> and ſtood upon their guard againſt her. Thirdly, the <hi>African</hi> Churches did the ſame. Fourthly, All thoſe ſuffering Churches and Chriſtians, that were oppreſſed under, and by the Papacy, as living within the reach of the Popes power.</p>
                  <p>Or, if we conſider the preſent ſtate of things, at this day, and in this Age, wherein we live, there be very many, with whom the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> hath broke communion: As for inſtance,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:33762:20"/>All the Chriſtians in <hi>Aſia,</hi> and <hi>Africa,</hi> except ſome late Colonies of <hi>Papiſts:</hi> All the <hi>Grecian</hi> Churches in <hi>Europe:</hi> All thoſe that are under the Patriarchs of <hi>Conſtantinople, Antioch, Alexandria, Jeruſalem, Ruſſia,</hi> and <hi>Muſcovia.</hi> Alſo the Proteſant Churches and Kingdoms, and many that lie hid under the Dominions of Popiſh Princes, who ſigh, and mourn, and groan under the Abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minations of the Papacy. Sir <hi>Edwin Sands,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Sir</hi> E S. <hi>Euro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pae Speculum,</hi> or view of the ſtate of Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in Weſtern parts, <hi>pag.</hi> 76. &amp; 187.</note> who was a great Traveller, and a very intelligent perſon, his computation in Q. <hi>Elizabeths</hi> time, was, That about one half of the Popes Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions, were fallen from him, and become Proteſtants, five of the Ten horns have begun to hate the Whore; And you know how that ſince thoſe dayes, you have not been gaining, but rather loſing ground; inſomuch, that when all Accompts are caſt up, both of thoſe who were never ſubject to the Pope, and thoſe who have ſhaken off his yoke, it will be found, That the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> is not a third part of the Chriſtian world. All theſe Companies ſhe hath left, and gone out from all theſe Bodies, and Societies of Chriſtians; hence therefore:</p>
                  <p n="1">1. It is a ſtrange Queſtion for you to ask, <hi>Whoſe Company ſhe hath left?</hi> For you cannot but know, if you know any thing at all of theſe matters, that there is a far greater number of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians out of her Communion and Juriſdiction, than are within it.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. This renders her aſſuming and monopolizing to her ſelf, the name and title of the Catholick Church, in oppoſition to all other Churches out of her Communion, not only falſe, but ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treamly vain, and (in plain terms) ridiculous: For is ſhe the whole Catholick Church, who is not a third part of it? Or rather, is not this a piece of Schiſmatical pride and arrogance in her? the very ſame with the <hi>Donatiſts</hi> of old, who did unchurch all others but themſelves, and ſo do you, which is not the Spirit of the Goſpel, but rather an evidence againſt you, that you have neither part nor lot in this matter, and that your hearts are not right in the fight of God, which are ſo full of the gall of bitterneſs, and ſharp cenſoriouſneſs.
<note place="margin">Ravn. 6. <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſo Concl,</hi> 5. pa. 687.</note> It further confirms that which hath been long ago demonſtrated unto you, by that Learned <hi>Raynolds, That the Church of</hi> Rome <hi>is not the Catholick Church, nor yet a ſound Member of the Catholick Church.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And ſo much for the <hi>Apoſtaſies, Hereſies,</hi> and <hi>Schiſms</hi> of your Church; The next thing in your paper is this:</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:33762:21"/>
               <head>CHAP. VI. <hi>Some places of Scripture for the Inerrability of the Church of</hi> Rome, <hi>Anſwered.</hi>
               </head>
               <div type="discourse">
                  <head>DISCOURSE.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>THe uſual colour of believing more or leſs, than the Church allows, is vain and erroneous; inaſmuch, as that very Chriſt, that ſtored her with knowledge of Gods revealed Truth, and with power to convey the ſame, hath alſo endued her with Inerrability to convey the ſame juſtly, without danger of miſcarrying, againſt Ignorance.</hi> To you it is given to know the myſteries of heaven, <hi>Matt.</hi> 13.11. <hi>Againſt darkneſs;</hi> Ye are the light of the world, <hi>Matt.</hi> 5.14. <hi>Againſt error and falſhood;</hi> I will ſend unto you the Spirit of truth, to remain with you for ever, <hi>John</hi> 14.16. <hi>Againſt weakneſs;</hi> She is the pillar and ground of truth, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3. Hell-gates ſhall not prevail againſt her, <hi>Matt.</hi> 16.18, &amp;c.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="answer">
                  <head>ANSWER.</head>
                  <p>Now to examine the Contexture of this Diſcourſe, though ſomething might be ſaid, both to the Grammar, and Logick of it, nor the ſoundneſs and ſenſe of thoſe diſtinctions you ſeem to make between Ignorance and Darkneſs (for what is moral Darkneſs, but Ignorance?) and Error and Falſhood, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Your Scope is, to aſſert the Authority, and Inerrability of your Church, as the ſupreme Rule of Faith and Obedience. But what you mean by the Church, whether Popes, or General Councils, you ſay not, you know your Writers are divided a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout it. But to the Scriptures you alledge, we need not (as you ſay we muſt) but through the help of his grace, we will not impeach either the power or faithfulneſs of Chriſt; but there be three other things, which we may truly, and fitly ſay to you concerning thoſe Scriptures.</p>
                  <pb n="35" facs="tcp:33762:21"/>
                  <p n="1">1. That you do not ſhew particularly, where their pertinen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy lies, or how you would apply them to the point you aim at, they being in their plain and genuine ſenſe, moſt remote from it.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. That they do not prove Inerrability in thoſe, to whom they were ſpoken and intended; for they are as applicable to every other Church, yea, to every true Believer, as to the Church of <hi>Rome:</hi> For every true Believer hath the Spirit of Grace and Truth dwelling in him, and is inlightned thereby, to know the myſteries of the Kingdom of Heaven; but yet it doth not fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, nor will you affirm, That every true Believer, that every godly Man, and every godly Woman, is infallible.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. We anſwer, further, That theſe Promiſes and Scriptures were not given to the Pope and Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> there is no pretence nor colour for it. How ill doth it become you, who do deny the perſeverance of true Believers, to claim to your ſelves an intereſt in ſuch promiſes, that the Spirit ſhall remain with you for ever? It was never ſaid to the Pope, <hi>Ye are the light of the world:</hi> For he is indeed the Angel of Death, the Meſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger and Inſtrument of Darkneſs; a Star fallen from Heaven, who hath opened the bottomleſs pit, and overſpread the whole face of the viſible Church, with ſmoke and darkneſs, as was prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſied of him, in the fifth Trumpet, <hi>Revel.</hi> 9.1. It was not ſaid to the Pope, <hi>What ye bind on Earth, ſhall be bound in Heaven; and to you it is given to know the myſteries of Heaven: or that I will ſend the Spirit to you, to remain with you for ever.</hi> It was not ſaid to him, nor to the <hi>Roman Catholick viſible Church.</hi> You have been told ſo an Hundred times. You have been challenged an Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred times over, to prove your intereſt in theſe promiſes, if you can: And now again, if you reply to this paper, what ever you paſs by in ſilence, yet I pray remember this, That you prove your intereſt in them, now once at laſt. And to provoke you, if poſſible, thereunto, give me leave to tell you, That howſoever you labour to put a good face upon the matter, yet there are not wanting appearances and grounds of diffidence, even among your ſelves about it; for <hi>Bellarmine</hi> numbers the alligation of the Apoſtolick See to <hi>Rome,</hi> in no higher rank, than that of pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, and very probable Opinions.
<note place="margin">B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ll. <hi>de Rom. Pontif. lib.</hi> 4. <hi>cap.</hi> 4.</note> 
                     <hi>Quod non ſit omnino de fide à Romana Eccleſia non poſſe ſeparari Apoſtolicam ſedem patet, quia ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que Scriptura, neque traditio habet ſedem Apoſtolicam ita fixam eſſe
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:33762:22"/>Romae, ut inde auferri non poſſit nibilominus tamen pia &amp; pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>babiliſſima eſt ſententia.</hi> But if the Apoſtolick ſeat be remove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able from <hi>Rome,</hi> then by your own principles ſhe may erre and periſh: Therefore, I ſay again, prove your intereſt in any Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture-promiſe, if you can.</p>
                  <p>Do it if you can (for inſtance) concerning that famous Text, upon which you found your claim, <hi>Matt.</hi> 16.18. <hi>Thou art</hi> Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, <hi>and upon this Rock will I build my Church, and the gates of Hell ſhall not prevail againſt it.</hi> This Text belongs as much to <hi>Maho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>met,</hi> as to the Pope; you would fain give it to the Pope, but how many <hi>poſtulata</hi> muſt you beg without proof, before you can arrive at ſuch a concluſion? as,</p>
                  <p n="1">1. That <hi>Peter</hi> was at <hi>Rome.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2. That he was there martyred, and marthered by the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">3. That the murthering of an honeſt man, doth give the Thief that did it, a juſt right and title to all his Eſtates and Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours;
<note place="margin">Cartwr. <hi>on Matth.</hi> 16.18.</note> or, as Mr. <hi>Cartwright</hi> ſpeaketh, That innocent blood, which polluteth other places, ſhould ſanctifie <hi>Rome;</hi> and that the Lord, who in revenge threw down <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> from her privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges, which ſhe had above all the Cities in the world, for ſpil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling the blood of the Prophets, ſhould in reward lift up the head of <hi>Rome,</hi> above all other Cities, for ſhedding the blood of the Apoſtles: Nay, rather, foraſmuch as it was more drunken with the blood of Saints, under the Government of the Emperors, than ever was any, and therein hath juſtified, her elder ſiſter <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem,</hi> therefore by the moſt juſt judgment of God, it is become the Seat of Antichriſt. Yea, by this Argument, as he alſo ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves, <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> that killed our Saviour Chriſt himſelf, getteth the prize from her.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. That <hi>Peter</hi> was Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> which was inconſiſtent with his Office of Apoſtleſhip.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. That he left a Succeſſor <hi>in eodem gradu,</hi> in his Apoſtolical power and office; that whereas the Commiſſion was perſonal to the reſt to determine with themſelves, he onely of all the Twelve ſhould hold the Apoſtleſhip, as it were, in fee-ſimple, for him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, and his Succeſſors for ever.</p>
                  <p n="6">6. That the Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> is this Succeſſor, though <hi>Peter</hi> taught at <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> firſt,
<note place="margin">Cartwr. <hi>on Matth</hi> 16.18.</note> afterwards at <hi>Lidda,</hi> then at <hi>Joppa,</hi> af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards at <hi>Antioch,</hi> and likewiſe at <hi>Caeſarea,</hi> laſtly, at <hi>Alexan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dria,</hi>
                     <pb n="37" facs="tcp:33762:22"/>before he came to <hi>Rome:</hi> And ſo the Apoſtolical Authority is holden by the tenure of <hi>Burrow Engliſh,</hi> where the youngeſt enjoyeth all, as Mr. <hi>Cartwright</hi> there obſerves.</p>
                  <p>Of all which ſuppoſitions, the two firſt are meerly diſputable and uncertain, and can never be demonſtrated, but the four laſt are moſt certainly and indiſputably ſalſe. But yet all theſe we muſt believe, to the end we may believe the Popes concernment in this promiſe made to <hi>Peter.</hi> And many a child of God have you offered in the fire to <hi>Molech,</hi> for not believing theſe <hi>Roman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces:</hi> But when will you go about to prove them? You know in your own Conſciences, that there is as much footing in the Scripture for the old <hi>Pagan Theogonie,</hi> their Pedigrees and Fables of their Canonized Anceſtors, and for the <hi>Jewiſh Thalmudick,</hi> as for theſe <hi>Romantick</hi> Figments. Learned men have obſerved, That there may be ſome dark footſteps of the true Scripture Hiſtory of <hi>Adam,</hi> inveſtigated, and diſcerned in the old Heathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh Fable of <hi>Saturn;</hi> ſome footſteps of the Hiſtory of <hi>Cham</hi> and <hi>Cain</hi> in the Fables of <hi>Jupiter,</hi> of <hi>Noah</hi> in <hi>Bacchus,</hi> of <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> and <hi>Joſeph</hi> in <hi>Mercurius Triſmegiſtus,</hi> of <hi>Joſhuah</hi> and <hi>Sampſon</hi> in <hi>Hercules,</hi> &amp;c. And truly there is no more of <hi>Peter</hi> the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle, in the Pope of <hi>Rome;</hi> thoſe being nothing elſe, but depra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vations of, and depraved Traditions, and Additions to, the Truths and Sacred Hiſtories of the Old Teſtament, and ſo is <hi>Popery</hi> to the New. You reaſon from the promiſe made to <hi>Peter,</hi> that the Church cannot fail, being builded upon a Rock; nor, needs no new Maſons, to re-build her again: But why do you not prove the <hi>Roman</hi> Synagogue to be a Church? You know we de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny it, otherwiſe then as the dead carcaſs, or picture of a man, is called a man; She is <hi>Eccleſia malignantium,</hi> as <hi>Pſal.</hi> 26.5. A Church of evil doers, but not a true Goſpel Church, not a Spouſe of Chriſt. Though if ſhe were, yet a true Church, when declining, or defective, may need Inſtruments in the hand of Chriſt to Reform her; call them new Maſons, or by what other name of honour or contempt you pleaſe. Therefore, after the renewed promulgation of the Goſpel, in the tenth <hi>Chapter</hi> of the <hi>Revelations,</hi> Chriſt doth authorize and commiſſionate his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants to meaſure the Temple, and to leave out the outer Court, <hi>Revel.</hi> 11.1, 2. which importeth ſome further degree of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation; but prove the Pope, and Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> to be at all concerned, in what was ſaid, to <hi>Peter,</hi> if you can.</p>
                  <pb n="38" facs="tcp:33762:23"/>
                  <p>Do it, if you can; concerning that other Scripture, ſo much abuſed by you, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.15. The Church is the pillar and ground of Truth, becauſe by the Miniſtry of the Church, the Truth is publiſhed and propagated;
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Mr.</hi> Bedle<hi>'s Letters to</hi> Wadſworth. <hi>cap.</hi> 8. <hi>p.</hi> 118.</note> as if a Law, or Procla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of the King be ſet up, upon a pillar in the Market-place; or in alluſion, as Mr. <hi>Bedle</hi> takes it, to the <hi>baſes</hi> or pillars that held up the Vail or Curtains in the Tabernacle: And whether you refer it to <hi>Timothy</hi> as ſome, or to the <hi>Church</hi> as others, it comes much to one. Evident it is, that the Apoſtle ſpeaks it directly, either of <hi>Timothy,</hi> or of the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Epheſus;</hi> and that it holds by a parity of reaſon, concerning all other Goſpel Miniſters, and Goſpel Churches, both the one, and the other, may be called in a ſafe ſenſe, the pillar and ground of truth. But what is this to the Church of <hi>Rome? How ridiculous a reaſon were it</hi> (ſaith Mr. <hi>Cartwright</hi>) <hi>for the Apoſtle to exhort</hi> Timothy <hi>to walk circumſpectly in the Church of</hi> Epheſus,
<note place="margin">Cartwr. <hi>in locum.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>becauſe the Church of</hi> Rome <hi>is thepillar and ſtablement of truth?</hi> The Papiſts (ſaith <hi>Calvin</hi>) <hi>dum ad ſe transferunt hoc encomium, improbe faciunt, alienis ſe plu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mis veſtiendo. Nam ut evehatur Eccleſia ſupra tertium Coelum, nego id totum ad eos ullomodo pertinere.
<note place="margin">Calvin <hi>in loc.</hi>
                        </note> Quinetiam locum preſentem ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſus eos retorqueo: nam ſi Eccleſia columna eſt veritatis, ſequitur non eſſe apud eos Eccleſiam, ubi non modo ſepulta jacet veritas, ſed hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rendum in modum diruta &amp; everſa ſub pedibus calcatur.</hi> When the <hi>Papiſts</hi> transfer this glory to themſelves, they do wickedly, cloathing themſelves with the feathers of other Birds: For, ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe the Church be extolled, and lifted up above the Third Heavens, I deny, that any thing of all this excellency belongs in the leaſt to them; yea, further, I retort this place againſt them: For, if the Church be the Pillar of Truth, then it follows, that the Church is not amongſt them, where the Truth doth not only, lie buried, but is torn down, and overthrown, and tramp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led under foot, in a fearful manner. <hi>An hoc eſt vel aeuigma, vel ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>villum? Paulus Eccleſiam non vult agnoſci, niſi in qua excelſa &amp; conſpicua ſtat Dei veritas in Papatu nihil tale apparet, ſed diſiectio tantùm &amp; ruinae, ergo genuina Eccleſiae nota illic non extat.</hi> Is there any difficulty, or any cavilling in this! <hi>Paul</hi> will not have any Church acknowledged, but ſuch as wherein the Truth of God ſtands on high, conſpicuous to the view of all men. But there is no ſuch thing to be ſeen in the <hi>Papacy,</hi> but the overthrow and ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ines of the Truth; therefore there is no true note, or mark of the Church to be found there.</p>
                  <pb n="39" facs="tcp:33762:23"/>
                  <p>The plain Truth is, That Apoſtate Church, and the Head thereof, that is <hi>Babylon,</hi> and Antichriſt, hath no right to any one promiſe in the Book of God, but ſtands directly under all the Threatnings and Curſes written therein, becauſe they have both added thereto, and taken from it, <hi>Revel.</hi> 22.18, 19. Indeed thoſe Churches, and thoſe Souls, have the beſt right to the promiſes, that prize them moſt: Therefore the Proteſtant Churches have a better right to them, than the Church of <hi>Rome.</hi> By the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant Churches, I intend, all that do ſubject themſelves to the Scripture, as the Rule of Faith and Life: And by the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> all thoſe that ſuffer the Pope to have dominion over their Faith; for we do not judge every Individual in the exter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal communion of that Church, but onely ſuch of them as have drunk down her deadly poyſon; What have they to do with the promiſes? What have they to do with God, to take his Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant into their mouths? Who do believe in a man that can lye? and in a Church of men, who may deceive, and be deceived? How much better and ſafer would it be for your eternal peace, to cleave to the Scriptures, which are the voyce of God, and ſo to bottom and ground your Faith upon the truth and faithful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of him that cannot lye, then thus to ground it upon a man that ſhall dye, and upon the ſons of men, that ſhall be made as graſs: <hi>For all fleſh is as graſs, and all the glory of man, as the flower of graſs; The graſs withereth, and the flower thereof fadeth away, but the Word of the Lord endureth for ever.</hi> And this is the Word which by the Goſpel is preached unto you.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <pb n="40" facs="tcp:33762:24"/>
               <head>CHAP. VII. <hi>Of Humane Teſtimonies, for and againſt the See of</hi> Rome.</head>
               <p>THat which remains of your Diſcourſe, is partly Quota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, without ſo much as attempting to prove your in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt in them, of ſome parallel Texts with thoſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore anſwered; partly repetitions of thoſe impertinent Queries, <hi>Whether did the Roman Church go from any other known Church,</hi> &amp;c? Anſwered alſo before, under the Head of <hi>Schiſm,</hi> partly Humane Teſtimonies for the See of <hi>Rome,</hi> for ſo you phraſe it, the Body of your Diſcourſe having run upon this ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion, the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> the Title being the <hi>Roman</hi> Faith. To your Humane Teſtimonies, I would humbly offer three things to your ſerious conſideration, which, I ſuppoſe, may ſuffice to all you ſay, or can ſay, from the Fathers, in whom you ſeem to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe your greateſt confidence, for the defence of your cauſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Conſid.</hi> 1. That you know we do not own the Fathers, but the Scriptures onely, as the Supreme Judge of Controverſies: Though we honour them, as bleſſed Inſtruments in their Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration; yet we know they were but men, and not Apoſtles in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallibly, inſpired and aſſiſted by the Holy Ghoſt, Yea, we do in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genuouſly acknowledge, That the darkneſs, and inadvertency of the Fathers in ſome points, did contribute and make way for the riſe and growth of Popery. They had their hands ſo full of other work, partly from without, in all their Conflicts, both with <hi>Jews</hi> and <hi>Pagans,</hi> both by writing and ſuffering, while the Chriſtian Princes alſo in the mean time, were not idle, but had their hands full, in the Wars of <hi>Michael</hi> againſt the Dragon, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the perſecuting <hi>Pagan</hi> Emperors, during that fourth Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tury: And partly from within, by thoſe inteſtine miſchiefs, which, through the malice and craft of Sathan, were bred within the Churches own bowels, ſuch as <hi>Arrianiſm,</hi> with all the Errors and Blaſphemies accompanying and flowing from it, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Perſon and Natures of Chriſt, and againſt his bleſſed
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:33762:24"/>Spirit. As alſo <hi>Pelagianiſm,</hi> wretchedly undermining the work of his Grace and Spirit, in the effectual application of Chriſt, and his redeeming Love, to the Souls of his Elect. <hi>Donatiſm</hi> likewiſe at the ſame time dreadfully diſturbing the peace, and order, and fellowſhip of the Goſpel, by diſchurching, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptiſing all other Chriſtians, and re-baptiſing themſelves, whil'ſt othres in the mean time wereas much too large, and looſe, as they too rigid. The faithful Servants of Chriſt were thus aſſaulted in thoſe dayes on every ſide, over and beſide the daily work of Teaching and Governing their reſpective Flocks and Churches. All which, did ſo ſeverely call upon them for their deepeſt intentions and endeavours, that as it rendred the work heavy upon the ſhoulders of the faithful Miniſtry in thoſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicting times, ſo, truly, to my narrow capacity, it is no wonder, if in the mean time, the deep and ſubtile workings of the my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery of Iniquity in the Papacy, did, in a great meaſure, eſcape their obſervation. And the rather, if we conſider the diſad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage they were under, both for want of Printing, and of well regulated and formed Univerſities and Schools of the Prophets. The Monaſtick Inſtitutions at firſt (as ſome have thought) coming neareſt, and ſeeming to have had ſome glimpſe and aim thereat; ſo that when all accounts are caſt up, aſſuredly it will be found, That we have more cauſe to acknowledge and admire the grace and power of Chriſt, in acting and enabling his ſervants to ſee ſo much, and go ſo far, in thoſe dark and difficult times, then to ſtumble at the diſpenſation of his Providence, becauſe they did not ſee every thing. Neither have you for your parts, either cauſe or colour to offend at theſe ſentiments of ours concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Fathers, when your own <hi>Petavius</hi> can ſay,
<note place="margin">Petav. <hi>Ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>madv. in E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piph. Haereſ.</hi> 69 <hi>Arriano rum.</hi> p. 285.</note> Pleriſque ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terum patrum—uſu venit ut ante Errorum atque Haereſeon— Originem, quibus Chriſtianae fidei capita ſingillatim oppugna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bantur, nondum ſatis illuſtrata ac patefactâ rei veritate, quae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam ſuis ſcriptis aſperſerint, quae cum orthodoxae fidei regulâ minime conſentiant. <hi>It is a common thing</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>with moſt of the ancient Fathers, that before the riſe of Errors and Hereſies, whereby the Articles of the Chriſtian Faith were particularly oppugn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed (the truth of the thing being not fully enough cleared and laid o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen) they did intermingle ſome things in their Writings, which do not agree with the rule of the Orthodox Faith.</hi> Thus he; yea, there is nothing more common with your Writers, than to cry
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:33762:25"/>the Fathers either up or down, meerly as may ſerve their turn, and that ſometimes in term; courſe enough. <hi>Patres quos ſe ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerari ſimulat,</hi> ſaith <hi>Beza,</hi> concerning your Church, <hi>Palam tamen imperitis illudens conculcat.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Beza <hi>in</hi> 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.15.</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Conſid.</hi> 2. You may do well to conſider yet further, That the Fathers did bear their Teſtimony ſo far as their Light ſerved a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the corruptions they ſaw coming in; though in ſome things, which it pleaſed God in his unſearchable wiſdom to hide from them, they did run with the Cry, and ſay, as others ſaid; yet, in other things, they bear witneſs againſt you. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it were eaſie to retaliate, and requite you with as many Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimonies of the Ancients on the other hand, againſt the See of <hi>Rome,</hi> as you have brought for it: You may ſee a little handful of them in <hi>Calvins</hi> Preface to his <hi>Inſtitutions.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>As to thoſe ſpeeches you quote, as ſounding for you out of <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piphanius, Auſtin,</hi> and <hi>Ambroſe,</hi> you ſeem to underſtand their words in a deeper ſenſe, than ever they intended them; for what though the Ancients ſometimes called <hi>Peter</hi> the Chief, the Firſt, the Head, the Prince of the Apoſtles, yet theſe, and ſuch like Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taphors, may be underſtood in ſuch a modified ſenſe, as to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port no more but only a precedency of order, and not a ſuprema<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of power; the former whereof, is granted by our Divines to <hi>Peter,</hi> but will ſtand you in no ſtead; and the latter you cannot prove, though if you could, yet this alſo would not do your buſineſs; for, ſuppoſe <hi>Peter</hi> had been as great a King as <hi>Solomon,</hi> yet what is this to the <hi>Pope,</hi> any more than to the <hi>Turk,</hi> or to the King of <hi>Spain?</hi> But it will be difficult for you to evince, with cogency of demonſtration, That the preference the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers give him, doth amount to any further or higher power, than that of the Foreman of a Jury, or the Speaker of the Houſe of Parliament, or the Moderator of a Synod, who hath a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heminence of Order, but not of Power and Juriſdiction, above the reſt of his Colleagues. What ſay you to that of <hi>Jerom?</hi> Ut Plato Princeps Philoſophorum,
<note place="margin">Hieron. 2. <hi>lib. adverſ. Pelag.</hi>
                  </note> ita Petrus Apoſtolorum fuit; <hi>As</hi> Plato <hi>was Prince of the Philoſophers, ſo was</hi> Peter <hi>of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles:</hi> But <hi>Plato</hi> had no power of Government or Juriſdiction over other Philoſophers, but onely an eminency of eſteem and reſpect. I might here alſo tell you, as to <hi>Epiphanius</hi> (but that I haſten to a cloſe) that the Teſtimony you alledge, is not in his <hi>Anchoratus,</hi> but in his <hi>Panarium contra Haereſes.</hi> As alſo, what a
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:33762:25"/>Teſtimony he hath born againſt you, concerning your Idolatry;
<note place="margin">Vide <hi>infta Cap</hi> 8. <hi>Append.</hi>
                  </note> and how ſlightly your own Writers, ſuch as <hi>Canus, Baronius, Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tavius,</hi> are pleaſed to ſpeak of him.</p>
               <p>As to <hi>Auſtin,</hi> the firſt ſentence you quote from him, as it doth not occur in the place you quote, where I have ſearched for it, ſo neither indeed do I remember any ſuch expreſſion of his in any other place. The next, wherein he ſpeaks of <hi>Peter</hi> as the Rock, I wonder you would quote, when I preſume you are not ignorant, that he hath put it among his Retractations, and gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven a ſounder expoſition of the Rock concerning Chriſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf.
<note place="margin">Retract. <hi>lib.</hi> 1. <hi>cap.</hi> 21.</note> 
                  <hi>Dixi de Apoſtolo Petro quod in illo tanquam in Petra fundata ſit Eccleſia. Sed ſcio me poſtea ſic expoſuiſſe, ut ſuper hunc, intellige<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retur quem confeſſus eſt Petrus—Non enim dictum eſt illi tu es Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra, ſed tues Petrus. Petra autem erat Chriſtus.</hi> And again,
<note place="margin">Serm. 13. <hi>in Matth.</hi> p. 22. <hi>Edit. Lovan.</hi>
                  </note>— <hi>Aedificabo Eccleſiam meam, id eſt ſuper meipſum filium Dei vivi aedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficabo Eccleſium meam. Nam volentes homines aedificari ſuper bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mines, dicebant, ego quidem ſum Pauli, ego autem Apollo, ego vero Cephae.</hi> And that his <hi>Principatus Apoſtolici Sacerdotis,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Epiſ.</hi> 162.</note> and what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever other expreſſion of his, may ſeem to carry a benign aſpect towards the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> muſt be underſtood with ſome temper and allay, is undeniably evident by the famous Teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies, conſtantly born by him, and by the reſt of the <hi>African</hi> Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops and Councils, againſt the Incroachments and Uſurpations, of that aſpiring, and devouring See of <hi>Rome.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Can.</hi> 22:</note> The <hi>Milevitan</hi> Council decreed, <hi>Ad Tranſmarina qui putaverit appellandum, à nullo intra Africam in communionem ſuſcipiatur.</hi> If any man ſhall appeal beyond the Seas, let none in <hi>Africk</hi> receive him to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion. And in <hi>Cyprian</hi>'s time, upon occaſion of <hi>Stephanus</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> his interpoſing on the behalf of <hi>Baſilides,</hi> and <hi>Martialis,</hi> who had been depoſed for ſacrificing to Idols, <hi>Cypri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an,</hi> and other Biſhops in Council with him, decreed,
<note place="margin">Cypr. <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 55. <hi>Pamel.</hi>
                  </note> Ut unius cujuſque cauſa illic audiatur ubi eſt crimen admiſſum, &amp; illic agere cauſam ſuam, ubi &amp; accuſatores habere &amp; teſtes ſui cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minis poſſit. <hi>That every ones cauſe ſhould be heard in the place of the Fact committed, and there manage his cauſe—where the Defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant may have both accuſers and witneſſes face to face.</hi> So little underſtood they of the Popes Supremacy.</p>
               <p>As to <hi>Ambroſe,</hi> the Books you quote, <hi>De Vocatione Gentium,</hi> are generally concluded, by all Learned men, both Papiſts and Proteſtants, to be none of his; but ſome aſcribe them to <hi>Euche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:33762:26"/>Lugdunenſis. Bellarmine</hi> to <hi>Proſper;</hi> yet <hi>Voſſius</hi> thinks they are none of <hi>Proſpers,</hi> as differing from his principles, and ſo thinks <hi>J. Latius</hi> of them, as differing from his ſtile. <hi>Libros de Vocatione Gentium</hi> (ſaith <hi>Rivet) ſentiunt fere omnes non eſſe Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broſii.
<note place="margin">Riv. <hi>Crit. Sacr.</hi> lib. 3. cap. 17. <hi>&amp;</hi> lib. 4. cap. 18. <hi>Lat.</hi> lib. 2. <hi>de Semi Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lag.</hi> cap. 3.</note> Eraſmo ſtilus videtur non abhorrere à phraſi Eucherii Lug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dunenſis. Bellarminus &amp; alii fere omnes eos aſſerunt Proſpero, Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtare tamen, ſcribit clariſſimus Veſſius, quod illius Authoris ſententia non videtur quadrare cum doctrina Proſperi. A Proſperi etiam ſtilo abludere judicavit vir eruditus Joh. Latius.</hi> Moreover, ſeeing you mention <hi>Ambroſe,</hi> you may remember his judgment was, That <hi>Rome</hi> is <hi>Babylon,</hi> Apoc. 17. So much for this ſecond Conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, That the Fathers did teſtifie in part againſt you, and not ſo much for you, as you pretend.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Conſiderat.</hi> 3. I pray conſider in the third place, That there be many, even of your own Writers, that teſtifie againſt you in ſeveral things; for which, you have put their Names, and their Books, into your honeſt <hi>Indices Expurgatorii,</hi> and into your <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dex librorum prohibitorum,</hi> ſuch as <hi>Stella, Maſius Eſpencaeus, Ferus,</hi> &amp;c. But there be others left, who have eſcaped your Interpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations, Expurgations, and Prohibitions, who teſtifie againſt you to your faces. Let me add but two or three ſignal Inſtances to what you have had already.</p>
               <p>Firſt,
<note place="margin">Greg. <hi>lib.</hi> 6. <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 30. <hi>Lib.</hi> 4. <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 38. Bellarm. <hi>de Pontif.</hi> lib. 2. cap. 2. <hi>&amp;</hi> lib. 2. cap. 13. <hi>Ribera in A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poc.</hi> 14.8. Tertoll. <hi>cont. Judae.</hi> cap. 9. Aug. <hi>de Civ. Dei.</hi> lib. 18. cap. 22. Hieron. <hi>de Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritu ſanct. Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>log. &amp; Ep.</hi> 151, <hi>in Algaſ Qu.</hi> 11. Ambroſ. <hi>in Apoc.</hi> 17.</note> You know how ſharply Pope <hi>Gregory</hi> the firſt, inveighs againſt that proud, ſwelling, ſmoky title of Univerſal Paſtor, u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed and claimed by all his Succeſſors to this day. Ego autem fidenter dico, quia quiſquis ſe univerſalem vocat vel vocari de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderat, in elatione ſua Antichriſtum praecurrit, quia ſuperbiendo caeteris ſe praeponit. <hi>I ſpeak it confidently</hi> (ſaith he, and the Pope, you ſay, cannot erre) <hi>that whoſoever calls himſelf, or deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth to be called by others, univerſal Biſhop, or Paſtor, is the Fore-run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of Antichriſt, in his elation of mind, becauſe he lifts up himſelf in pride above others.</hi> And he ſaith, That it is a prophane Title, and that the King of pride is at the door, and an Army of Prieſts ready to fight his Battels, with many other ſuch like expreſſions.</p>
               <p>Secondly, I might here alſo tell you, how that <hi>Bellarmine</hi> and <hi>Ribera,</hi> both Jeſuites, and ſome others of the ſame Tribe, do confeſs and maintain, and that according to the judgement of ſundry of the Fathers, <hi>viz. Tertullian, Auſtin, Jerom, Ambroſe,</hi> That myſtical <hi>Babylon</hi> in the <hi>Revelations,</hi> is <hi>Rome,</hi> and that ſhe is reſerved and devoted to deſtruction, even to be burnt with fire.
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:33762:26"/>A conceſſion of more dangerous conſequence, and importance to your cauſe and intereſt, then to be evaded by <hi>Romances</hi> of an imaginary Antichriſt of the Tribe of <hi>Dan.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thirdly, If you ask for Humane Teſtimonies againſt that Scor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pion Doctrine of Juſtification by the merit of your own Works, and Penances, and Satisfactions, wherewith your Locuſts uſe to ſting and torment, and torture the Conſciences of men, worſe then Death; and upon which, as was ſaid before, that Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pion of the Lord, did pitch the Field againſt you; it is worth your noting, how <hi>Bellarmine</hi> having wreſtled, with his wit, in five Books againſt the truth of God, yet, at laſt (God confounding him in his oppoſition to it) he confeſſeth,
<note place="margin">Bell. <hi>de Juſtif.</hi> lib, 5. cap. 7. prop. 3.</note> 
                  <hi>Propter incertitudinem propriae juſtitiae, &amp; periculum inanis gloriae, Tutiſſimum eſt totam fiduciam in ſola Dei miſericordia &amp; benignitate reponere.</hi> Becauſe of the uncertainty of our own Righteouſneſs, and the danger of Vain-glory, it is the ſafeſt way to put our whole truſt in the meer mercy and goodneſs of God. And it is ſo indeed: But then <hi>Bellarmine,</hi> why did you diſpute againſt it? againſt the inward workings and recoylings of your own Conſcience, which did whiſper you in the ear, and told you, That this is the beſt and ſafeſt way, <hi>Ex ore tuo ſerve nequam.</hi> I cannot but often think of this paſſage of his, as one of the greateſt triumphs in this kind, that ever truth had, out of the mouth of ſuch an impetuous Adverſary; for <hi>magna eſt veritas, &amp; praevalebit.</hi> Surely theſe words of his do as well deſerve to be blotted out by an <hi>Index Expurgatorius,</hi> as thoſe of <hi>Chryſoſtom,
<note place="margin">Index <hi>Expurg. Litera C. Chryſoſtom.</hi> Index <hi>Expurg. Cardinal. Qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rega in litera B. Biblia</hi> Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berti Stephani.</note> Meritum nullum eſſe niſi quod à Chriſto confertur,</hi> which you have ordered to be purged out of his works, and as well as thoſe paſſages out of <hi>Robert Stephens</hi> Table to his Bible, <hi>Credendo in Chriſtum remittuntur peccata;</hi> and <hi>Credens Chriſto non morietur in aeternum; fide purifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cantur corda; juſtificamur fide in Chriſtum.</hi> Our ſins are forgiven, by believing in Chriſt; he that believeth in Chriſt, ſhall not dye eternally; our hearts are purified by ſaith; we are juſtified by ſaith in Chriſt; of which your pious <hi>Index</hi> ſaith, <hi>Deleantur ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jectae propoſitiones, tanquam ſuſpectae.</hi> Let theſe propoſitions be blotted out, as being ſuſpitious; for, it ſeems, you ſuſpect the very words of Scripture, and the Goſpel it ſelf, whether it be true or no; but there is nothing renders your Religion more ſuſpitious, and more odious unto my heart, then this your en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity unto the free grace of God, and againſt the Scripture, by
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:33762:27"/>which it is revealed, which you are ſtill venting upon all occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Matth.</hi> 19.16.</note> 
                  <hi>Coelum gratis non accipiam,</hi> ſaith <hi>Vega, I will not accept of heaven upon terms of free grace.</hi> But when death appears, and ſtares upon you, ſome of you can ſpeak at another rate; ſo did <hi>Bellarmine,</hi> when he prayed upon his Death-bed, <hi>Precor ut me Deus,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Fuligatus in vita</hi> Bellar. <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferente. Dr.</hi> Grew <hi>of Juſtif.</hi> pag. 91.169.</note> inter ſanctos, &amp; electos ſuos, non eſtimator meriti, ſed veniae largitor admittat.</hi> I pray, that God would receive me among his Saints, and choſen ones; not upon the account of merit, but for the ſake of his own pardoning grace and mercy. So <hi>Stephen Gardiner,</hi> when Dr. <hi>Day,</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Chicheſter,</hi> came to ſee him on his Death-bed, and began to comfort him with the words of Gods promiſes, and with the free juſtification in the blood of Chriſt our Saviour:
<note place="margin">Fox<hi>'s Acts and Mon.</hi> Vol. 3. page 527. col. 2.</note> 
                  <hi>Gardiner</hi> hearing that, <hi>What, my Lord,</hi> (quoth he) <hi>Will you open that Gap now, then farewell altogether; To me, and ſuch other in my caſe you may ſpeak it; but open this win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow to the people, then farewell altogether.</hi> Here were clear convi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, but ſtrange rebellion of ſpirit againſt them: And to leave this head,
<note place="margin">Voet. <hi>Vol.</hi> 2. <hi>Diſput</hi> 47. pag. 726.</note> 
                  <hi>Voetius</hi> hath a large and learned Diſpute with this Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle, <hi>Vis veritatis in ipſo papatu crumpentis, de ſalute per ſolam Dei miſericordiam in Chriſto.</hi> Wherein he produceth a cloud of Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes to this truth.</p>
               <p>It was alſo in my thoughts to have noted ſomething out of your own Writers concerning the Popiſh Circle, I mean, the maze of unbelief, wherein they run round, to prove the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture by the Church, and the Church back again by the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture: Like men drunk, and giddy with the cup of the Wine of Aſtoniſhment, and with the ſpirit of Deluſion; it being juſt with God to ſmite them with a vertiginous diſtemper of mind, that they ſhall never come to any conſiſtence, to any ſettlement in the Faith, who will not ſettle upon the true foundation, and acquieſce in the Scriptures of Truth. <hi>For as the fire devoureth the ſtubble, and the flame conſumeth the chaffe, ſo their root ſhall be as rottenneſs, and their bloſſome ſhall go up as duſt: becauſe they have caſt away the law of the Lord of Hoſts, and deſpiſed the word of the holy One of</hi> Iſrael, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 5.24.</p>
               <p>And, finally, ſeeing you call ſo much for Humane Teſtimonies, I had thought to have offered ſome, which, I think, you will bluſh to read, out of your own Writers, concerning the Vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration you give to your Popes, your Repreſentative Chriſts, and Vice-gods; and yet withall, concerning the hideous prophane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:33762:27"/>of their Lives, and their Errability, yea, their actual erring Errors, damnably, and fundamentally deſtructive of the Faith, and all this out of your own approved Authors, out of whom I have obſerved and collected a few things, but theſe few are too many to be here inſerted. The Subject is ſo copious, that it requires an intire Tractate by it ſelf, therefore muſt be deferred, till ſome other occaſion do preſent: And in the mean time, ſo long as <hi>Gregories praecurſor Antichriſti,</hi> and ſo long as <hi>Bellarmines Tuliſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſimum eſt,</hi> remains upon Record among men, you may ſhut your mouths, and ceaſe your boaſtings of Humane Teſtimonies.</p>
               <div type="part">
                  <p>I Have now, according to the meaſure of Light and Grace recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, returned you an Anſwer to your Paper, ſomewhat largely, I confeſs, being deſired to anſwer it to the full, but yet as briefly as I could; yea, omitting many things which might have been, both truly and pertinently ſpoken. I find, that it hath been an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered twice before by more Learned pens, which, as it renders this Labour of mine leſs neceſſary, and, which I think might have been ſpared, had you not called with ſuch renewed impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunities for an Anſwer; ſo it renders you the more without excuſe, for that now you have the Truth againſt one oppoſition confirmed to you in the mouth of Three Witneſſes. Firſt, by Mr. <hi>Baxter,</hi> in his <hi>Key for Catholicks,</hi> printed <hi>Anno</hi> 1659, who received a great part of this your paper, in a Manuſcript ſent from <hi>Wolverhampton</hi> to <hi>Sturbridge,</hi> and hath inſerted it, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>futed it in his Book before mentioned, <hi>page</hi> 244. It hath been anſwered a ſecond time by Dr. <hi>Owen,</hi> in his Animadverſions on <hi>Fiat Lux,</hi> Cap. 2. page 59, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and in his Vindication of his Animadverſions, <hi>Cap.</hi> 4. <hi>page</hi> 48. <hi>&amp; deinceps.</hi> And yet now, after two Anſwers in print, you ſend the ſame words again (ſuch is the penury of your cauſe) in a Manuſcript, to a perſon of Honour in this Kingdom of <hi>Ireland,</hi> with a challenge to our Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines to anſwer it, which hath produced and drawn forth this third Anſwer to it, beſides all that hath been written in former times, as alſo of late by Dr. <hi>Stillingfleete,</hi> Mr. <hi>Poole,</hi> and others, though not to this individual paper, but upon occaſion of other oppoſitions, yet in defence of the ſame general Truth, and Cauſe of Chriſt againſt Popery.</p>
                  <p>O that He, who alone is able, would vouchſafe to bleſs both thoſe former, and theſe preſent endeavours, ſo as to undeceive
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:33762:28"/>and open your eyes, and convince you by his Spirit of the Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity of Vanities, that is in theſe pretenſions of Supremacy, In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>errability, and Indefectibility in your Church and Pope. The Lord awaken you out of theſe golden Dreams, before it be too late: Yea, I do believe through grace, and am perſuaded, That he will yet do it, by one means or other, for ſuch of you as do belong to the election of his grace: The ſame free and ſovereign grace that did pity, that did undeceive, and convince, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quer <hi>Paul,</hi> when in his full career of blind Zeal, and oppoſition, is able to convince, and over-power you. <hi>Father, forgive them, for they know not what they do.</hi> Now the Lord in mercy do it, That your Faith may not ſtand hereafter in the wiſdom of men, but in the power of God.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <pb n="49" facs="tcp:33762:28"/>
               <head>CHAP. VIII. An APPENDIX for the further Illuſtration of ſome things, which are but briefly hinted in the former Chapters.</head>
               <p>IN <hi>Cap.</hi> 2. of <hi>Apoſtaſie,</hi> and again, in <hi>Cap.</hi> 3. of <hi>Hereſie,</hi> men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is made of counſel given by Papiſts to the Pope. A Friend, to whom the Anſwer was communicated in Manu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcript, made ſome Inquiry about it, to whom a further Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count was ſent; which becauſe the ſame Inquiries are not un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likely to ariſe in the ſtudious Readers mind, is thought fit to be communicated.</p>
               <p>I find there were two papers of Advice preſented to the Pope in thoſe dayes, about the time of the Council of <hi>Trent,</hi> for the help and ſupport of the then declining Church of <hi>Rome;</hi> both which, give pregnant evidence againſt her, of her corruption, and departure from Apoſtolical, and primitive purity. The firſt to Pope <hi>Paul</hi> the Third, in the Year 1538. by Nine ſelect Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nals and Prelates, <hi>viz.</hi> Cardinal <hi>Contarenus,</hi> Cardinal <hi>Peter Thea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinus,</hi> afterwards Pope <hi>Paul</hi> the Fourth, Cardinal <hi>Sadolet,</hi> Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinal <hi>Reginald Poole</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> &amp;c. The Title is, <hi>Conſilium Delectorum Cardinalium &amp; Praelatorum de emendanda Eccleſia:</hi> This <hi>Novem-virale Concilium,</hi> was ſent by <hi>Nicholaus Cardinalis Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulanus,</hi> to a Prince in <hi>Germany,</hi> by whom it came to the hands of <hi>Luther,</hi> and <hi>Sturmius,</hi> and by their means was made publick. It is mentioned and quoted by <hi>Eſpenſaeus,</hi> a Popiſh Biſhop, a <hi>Sorbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſt,</hi> in his Commentaries on <hi>Titus</hi> 1. It was extant in the Book of the Councils, <hi>Tom</hi> 3. <hi>Concil. Edit. per Crab. Edit. Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon.</hi> 1551. But in all other Editions, <hi>Pontificiorum furto &amp; fraude deſideratur,</hi> ſaith Mr. <hi>Craſhaw,</hi> who Reprinted it <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don</hi> 1609.</p>
               <p>Theſe men do with ſomething of Ingenuity acknowledge, and adviſe to a Reformation of ſundry enormous Abuſes and Corru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptions in the Church of <hi>Rome;</hi> and they begin wiſely and faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully, at the fountain &amp; Well-head, telling the Pope plainly, Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipium horum malorum inde ſuiſſe quod nonnuili Pontifices tui
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:33762:29"/>Praedeceſſores, prurientes auribus ut inquit Apoſtolus Paulus co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acervarunt ſibi magiſtros ad deſideria ſua non ut ab eis diſcerent quod facerè deberent,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Page</hi> 2.</note> ſed ut eorum ſtudio &amp; calliditate inveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retur ratio quâ liceret id quod liberet.—Ex hoc fonte ſancte pater, tanquam ex equo Trojano, irrupêre in Eccleſiam Dei tot abuſus tam &amp; graviſſimi morbi, quibus nune conſpicim is eam ad deſperationem ſere ſalutis laboraſſe. <hi>The beginning of theſe E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viis</hi> (ſay they) <hi>hath been, that ſome of the Popes your Predeceſſors, having itching ears, as the Apoſtle</hi> Paul <hi>ſpeaks, have heaped up unto themſelves Teachers according to their own deſires; Not that they might learn from them what they ought to do, but that by their ſtudy and craft a way might be found out whereby it might be lawful to do what they liſt. From this fountain holy father, as from the</hi> Trojan <hi>horſe, have broke forth ſo many abuſes into the Church of God, and ſuch grievous Diſeaſes under which we now ſee her labouring almoſt unto deſperation of recovery.</hi> The Popes Infallibility, it ſeems, was no Article of their Faith. Then they proceed to inſtance in ſundry particulars,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Page</hi> 5. <hi>&amp; de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>ceps.</hi>
                  </note> as <hi>Caraleſſenes,</hi> in the Ordination of Clergy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, putting men both ignorant and vicious into Holy Orders, beſtowing Benefices and Eccleſiaſtical promotions upon them; Reſervations of Penſions, changing and chopping of Livings, Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>propriations, Pluralities, Non-reſidences, Exemptions and Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pediments laid upon Biſhops, in governing their Flocks, and pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhing of Sinners. The great degeneracy and corruptions of Religious Orders, Simony, and filthy Lucre, in the exerciſe of the Keyes. The ſcandals between Monks and Nuns. Vain Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophy in Schools, and Univerſities, teaching Impiety; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as, ſay they, <hi>Oſtenderent infirmitatem luminis naturalis in Quaeſtio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nibus pertinentibus ad Deum:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Page</hi> 12.</note> They ought to ſhew the weakneſs of the light of Nature in diſquiſitions about the things of God. They inſtance alſo Diſpenſations for Marriage within the degrees forbidden,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Page</hi> 16.</note> abſolving Simoniacks: <hi>In hac etiam urbe meretrices ut matronae incedunt, habitant etiam infignes aedes, corrigendus bic tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pis abuſus.</hi> In this City of <hi>Rome (ſay they)</hi> Whores go up and down as honourably, as chaſte Matrons; and they dwell in ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptuous Houſes, this ſhameful abuſe ought to be Reformed. Theſe are ſome of the main Heads of their Advice. <hi>Tollantur</hi> (ſay they) <hi>obteſtamur ſanctitatem tuam,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Page</hi> 11.</note> per ſanguinem Chriſti quo rede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit ſibi Eccleſiam ſuam eamque lavit eadem ſanguine, toliantur hae maculae.</hi> We do beſeech and obteſt your Holineſs, by the blood
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:33762:29"/>of Chriſt, wherewith he hath redeemed his Church unto him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, waſhing it with his own blood, we beſeech you let theſe ſpots and blemiſhes be taken away. But the Pope would reform nothing, but was <hi>like the deaf Adder, which ſtoppeth her ear: which will not hearken to the voyce of the charmers, though they charm ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſo wiſely. We would have healed</hi> Babylon, <hi>but ſhe could not be healed: forſake her, and let us go every one into his own countrey: for her judgment reacheth unto heaven, and is lifted up even to the skies,</hi> Pſal. 58.4, 5. Jer. 51.9.</p>
               <p>The other counſel was given to Pope <hi>Julius</hi> the Third, by three Biſhops met at <hi>Bononia.</hi> It is intituled, <hi>Conſilium quorun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam Epiſcoporum Bononiae congregatorum: quod de ratione ſtabiliendae Romanae Eccleſiae.</hi> Julio. 3. Pont. Mux. datum eſt. It is ſubſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed, <hi>Bononiae</hi> Octob. 20. Anno 1553. <hi>Sauctitatis tuae ſervi &amp; cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aturae devotiſſimae.</hi> (Your Holineſſes moſt devoted ſervants and creatures) <hi>Vincentius de durantibus Epiſe. Thermularum Brixi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enſis. Aegidius Falceta Epiſco. Caprulanus. Gerardus Buſdagrus Epiſc. Theſſalonicenſis.</hi> It was firſt publiſhed by <hi>Vergerius</hi> after his converſion. It is mentioned by <hi>Johannes Wolphius,</hi> in his <hi>Memorabilia.</hi> And, laſtly, Re-printed at <hi>London,</hi> out of Mr. <hi>Craſhaws</hi> Library, <hi>Anno</hi> 1613. Theſe Adviſers, like meer car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Polititians, do obſerve horrid Degeneraties and Abuſes; but inſtead of counſels tending to Reformation, they mend the matter ſo, as to make it much worſe; their propoſals aiming at no other ſcope, but meerly how their ſins, and corrupt ſtate, which they love, and like ſo well, may be continued and preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, and how Light and Reformation may be kept out; ſome of their words being rendred in Engliſh, in the Anſwer a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove, <hi>Chapter</hi> 3. But moſt of the Latin omitted, for Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vities ſake; I ſhall here ſubjoin it, with ſome more alſo of their own words, for the Readers more ample ſatisfaction: <hi>Thus then they ſpeak.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Cum nos multum ac diu cogitaviſſemus quiſnam eſſet gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſſimae hujus controverſiae ſtatus—tandem hunc eſſe deprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dimus. Lutherani Symboli Apoſtolorum Niceni &amp; Athanaſii articulos omnes recipiunt &amp; confitentur.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Folio</hi> 1.</note> Atque id veriſſimum eſt. Neque enim inficiari oportet praeſertim inter nos, quod adeo verum eſſe omnes intelliginius. Itidem Lutherani negant velle ſe aliam doctrinam admittere, praeter unicam illam, quae prophetas Chriſtum &amp; Apoſtolos authores habet; optarentque
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:33762:30"/>ut pauciſſimis illis contenti eſſemus—Et priſcas Eccleſias imita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remur nec de recipiendis ullis traditionibus cogitaremus,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Folio</hi> 2.</note> quas non conſtat luce meridianâ clariu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s fuiſſe à Domino noſtro Jeſu Chriſto, &amp; abipſis Apoſtolis dictatas atque inſtitutas. Ita ſenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unt adverſarii noſtri.—Nos contra ſeculi opinionem beatitudinis tuae volumus credi—id quod in Decreto tertiae Seſſionis Conci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lium Tridentinum—ſtatuit; nempe Chriſtum atque ipſius A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtolos multo plura tum ad mores, tum ad fidem pertinentia docuiſſe—quam ea quae ſcripta ſunt. Et tametſi hoc aperte probare non poſſimus (nam planè fatemur inter nos—tantum habemus conjecturas quaſdam) tamen confitemur eſſe verum quia ſic tenet Romana Eccleſia. Hic eſt in ſumma cardo totius controverſiae, hinc tumultus illi, hinc illa contentio.—Nam A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtolorum temporibus, ut verum tibi fateamur, ſed ſilentio o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pus eſt, vel aliquot annis poſt ipſos Apoſtolos, nulla vel papatus, vel Cardinalatus mentio erat, nec ampliſſimos illos reditus Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcopatuum &amp; Sacerdotiorum fuiſſe conſtat, nec templa tantis ſumptibus exſtruebantur, nec erant Monaſteria, nec Priores, nec Abbates, multo vero minus hae doctrinae, hae leges, hae conſuetu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dines, ſed neque imperium illud quod in Gentes, &amp; Nationes ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diè obtinemus. Quin omnes omnium Eccleſiarum Miniſtri Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manae non minus quam caeterarum, ultro Regibus, principibus, &amp; magiſtratibus parebant.—Nos Re probe examinatâ comperimus hanc Ecclefiae gloriam, authoritatem &amp; potentiam tunc primum exortam eſſe, cum in ea ſagaces &amp; ſolertes Epiſcopi praeeſſe caepê<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runt, qui per occaſionem à Caeſaribus contenderent, ut ſuâ au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritate at potentiâ primatum &amp; ſummam in alias Eccleſias po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtatem, penes hanc ſedem eſſe ſtatuerent.</p>
               <p>Praeterea Conſilium noſtrum eſſet, ut tua ſanctitas Cardinali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus &amp; Epiſcopis praeciperet, ut Logicam, Sophiſticam, Artemque Scholaſticam &amp; Metaphyſicam,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Folio</hi> 5.</note> item decretales, ſex Clemen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinas extravagantes, &amp; regulas Cancellariae, in ſua quiſque civita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te legiae doceri publice curent. Utinam legendis hujuſmodi libris homines ubique diligentius incubuiſſent. Neque enim res noſtrae in hujuſmodi deploratiſſimum ſtatum adductae eſſent. Sed hi contemptis melioribus iſtis diſciplinis Graecae &amp; Hebraicae linguae operam dare, &amp; mox Bibliorum verſionem ad Graecam &amp; Hebraicam veritatem exigere examinareque ac Theologiae &amp; Antiquis Eccleſiae doctoribus ſtudere caeperunt. Unde damna illa quae jam ſuſtinemus Omnia extitere. Quare danda erit o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pera
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:33762:30"/>ut ſtudiis iſtiuſmodi valere juſſis, Scholaſticam artem &amp; tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um jus Canonicum homines repetant quibus Theologiae ſtudia ſepulta pene atque obruta fuiſſe olim conſtat.—Decretalium, &amp;c meminimus at non item Decreti, eſt enim pernicioſus liber &amp; authoritatem tuam valde vehementer imminuit. Ita enim in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quit Canon qui incipit Transferunt 24. Q. 3. Immutant menda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cio veritatem, qui aliud praedicant quam ab Apoſtolis acceperunt. Hoc plane Lutheranum eſt axioma: Quid enim aliud quotidie inculcant noſtri adverſarii, quam ne latum quidem unguem lice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re ab his rebus quae Apoſtolis fuere in uſu recedere? At quis eſt ex noſtris qui non recedat ſaepe quotidie? Certe vix umbram quandam retinemus in noſtris Eccleſiis ejus Doctrinae &amp; Diſcipli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nae quae Apoſtolorum temporibus ſieut etiam initio attigimus flo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruerunt &amp; prorſus aliam accerſivimus.</p>
               <p>Denique quod inter omnia Conſilia quae nos hoc tempore dare poſſumus,
<note place="margin">Folio penult.</note> omnium graviſſimum ad extremum reſervavi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus. Oculi hîc aperiendi ſunt, omnibus nervis aduitendum erit ut quam minimum Evangelii poterit praeſertim vulgari lingua, in iis legatur civitatibus quae ſub tua ditione &amp; poteſtate ſunt, ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiatque tantillum illud quod in miſſa legi ſolet, nec eo amplius cuiquam mortalium legere liceat. Quamdiu enim pauculo illo homines contenti fuerunt tamdiu res tuae ex ſententia ſucceſsêre, eaedem<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> in contrarium labi caeperunt ex quo ulterius legi vulgo uſurpatum eſt. Hic ille in ſumma eſt liber qui praeter caeteros haſce nobis tempeſtates ac turbines conciliavit quibus prope ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>repti ſumus: Et ſane ſiquis illum diligenter expendat, deinde quae in noſtris fieri Eccleſiis conſueverunt ſingula ordine con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>templetur, videbit plurimum inter ſe diſſidere, &amp; hanc doctrinam noſtram ab illa prorſus diverſam eſſe, ac ſaepe contrariam etiam. Quod ſimulatque homines intelligant, à docto ſcilicet aliquo ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſariorum ſtimulati non ante clamandi finem faciunt, quam rem plane omnem divulgaverint, noſque inviſos omnibus reddiderint. Quare occultandae pauculae illae chartulae, ſed adhibitâ quâdam cautione &amp; dilige<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tiâ, ne ea res majores nobis turbas ac tumul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus excitet. This laſt Paragraph, let Engliſh ears hear it.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Laſt of all</hi> (ſay they) <hi>which we have reſerved to the laſt place, as the weightieſt of all the counſels that we can give at this time. Your eyes are here to be opened. You muſt endeavour, with all the power you have, that as little as can be of the Goſpel be read, eſpecially in the vulgar tongue, in thoſe Cities which are within your power and ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſdiction,
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:33762:31"/>but let that little which is wont to be read in the Maſs ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, and let it not be lawful for any mortal man to read any more than that. For as long as men were content with that little, your affairs ſucceeded according to your hearts deſire; but they began to decline, and go back, as ſoon as it came in uſe to read more of it. This is in ſum that Book, which above all others, hath brought upon us theſe ſtorms and whirlewinds, wherewith we are almoſt carried away head<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long. And truly if any man ſhall diligently weigh that Book, and then conſider diſtinctly all thoſe things which are wont to be done in our Churches, he will ſee that they differ very much the one from the other, and that this Doctrine of ours is altogether diverſe from that, yea, and oftentimes directly contrary to it. Which as ſoon as men underſtand, being ſtirred up by ſome Learned man amongſt the Adverſaries, they make no end of clamoring, till they have laid open the whole matter, and rendred us odious unto all. Wherefore thoſe few ſheets of paper muſt be hid, and kept out of ſight, but with ſome caution and dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence, leſt the very doing of this, ſhould increaſe the ſtorm, and bring yet greater troubles and tumults upon us.</hi> This is their advice, with other things <hi>ejuſdem farinae,</hi> too many to be here Tranſcribed. Ghoſtly counſel, of ghoſtly Fathers. Wherein, indeed, they ſtate the Controverſie between them and us aright, namely, That their departure from the Scripture, and our adherence to it, is that which hath begun and bred the Quarrel, and made the breach between them and us, and the name Proteſtant ariſe; then inſtead of trembling at his Word, and humbling themſelves to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form by that unerring Rule, they enter into open Rebellion and Conſpiracy againſt the Rule, to ſuppreſs it, and ſmother it, even in the ſpiritual Language of thoſe Rebels, Who ſay, <hi>Pſalme</hi> 2.3. <hi>Let us break their bands aſunder, and caſt away their cords from us:</hi> For which, <hi>he that ſits in heaven, laughs at them, and the Lord hath them in deriſion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I find both theſe counſels mentioned by Pope <hi>Paul</hi> the 4th, and Pope <hi>Clement</hi> the 8th, in their <hi>Index librorum prohibitorum,</hi> pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed by them in purſuance of the Decrees of the Council of <hi>Trent.</hi> The former, in the letter <hi>L.</hi> under this Title, <hi>Liber inſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptus, Conſilium de emendanda Eccleſia:</hi> And ſo Pope <hi>Paul</hi> the 4th, prohibits and condemns the Book, and Council, ſubſcribed by himſelf, when he was Cardinal <hi>Peter Theatin:</hi> As the like change of judgment upon change of intereſt is commonly obſerved in <hi>Aeneas Sylvius,</hi> when he came to be Pope <hi>Pius</hi> the 2d. The latter
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:33762:31"/>counſel is mentioned in the letter C. under this <hi>Italian</hi> Title, <hi>Conſiglio d'alicuui Veſcovi congregati in Bologna.</hi> The counſel of certain Biſhops met together in <hi>Bononia.</hi> This may ſuffice, as to a further Account of this matter.</p>
               <p>In Cap. 7. <hi>of humane Teſtimonies,</hi> mention is made of <hi>Epipha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius</hi> his Teſtimony againſt Idolatry, and of the freedom of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion uſed by ſundry <hi>Romaniſts</hi> concerning him, whereof take this further account. <hi>Epiphanius</hi> his words are theſe: Quando veniſſem ad villam, quae dicitur Anablatha—Inveni ibi velum pendens in foribus ejuſdem Eccleſiae tinctum atque depinctum,
<note place="margin">Epiph. <hi>Operae. tom.</hi> 2, <hi>Epiſt. ad</hi> Johan. Hiero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſol. <hi>page</hi> 317. <hi>Edit. Petav.</hi> 1622.</note> &amp; habens imaginem quaſi Chriſti vel ſancti cujuſdam, non enim ſatis memini cujus imago fuerit. Cum ergo hoc vidiſſem in Eccleſia Chriſti contra authoritatem Scripturarum, hominis pendere i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maginem, ſcidi illud, &amp; magis dedi conſilium cuſtodibus ejuſdem loci ut pauperem mortuum eo obvolverent, &amp; efferrent.—Precor ut Jubeas—in Eccleſia Chriſti ejuſmodi vela quae contra Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onem noſtram veniunt, non appendi. <hi>As we were going to</hi> Bethel (ſaith he) <hi>when I came to a Village called</hi> Anablatha, <hi>I found there a Vail hanging in the Church-door coloured and painted, and having an Image in it, as it were of Chriſt, or ſome Saint; for I do not well remember whoſe Image it was: Wherefore when I ſaw this, that the Image of a man hung in the Church of Chriſt contrary to the Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of the Scriptures, I tore it in pieces. And, moreover, I counſelled the Keepers of that place, to wrap up the dead body of a poor man in the ſaid Vail, and ſo to carry him forth to be buried. And I do beſeech you to give order, that there be no ſuch Vails hung up in the Church of Chriſt, which are contrary to our Religion.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Riv. <hi>Crit. Sacr.</hi> lib. 3. cap. 29. Waldenſ. <hi>Tom.</hi> 3. <hi>Lit.</hi> 19. Cap. 157. Bell. <hi>de Imag.</hi> lib. 2. cap. 9. Salmeron <hi>Comment.</hi> in 1 <hi>John.</hi> cap. 5: Diſ. 32. <hi>Sixt. Sinenſ.</hi> lib. 5. <hi>Annot.</hi> 247. Greg. <hi>Valent. de Idol.</hi> lib. 2. cap. 7.</note>
               </p>
               <p>He writes this to <hi>John</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and the Epiſtle is Tranſlated by <hi>Jerom,</hi> a ſign he liked it well; and ſo you have the Teſtimony of two Fathers together, both <hi>Epiphanius</hi> and <hi>Jerom:</hi> A Teſtimony ſo full and clear, that your Writers come forth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt it one way, but flie ſeven. Some of them, as <hi>Rivet</hi> notes, ſenſleſly affirming, That he ſpeaks it in regard of the <hi>Anthropo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morphites,</hi> ſo <hi>Tho. Waldenſis,</hi> as <hi>Bellarmine</hi> reports. Others, with as little ſenſe, or reaſon, would have this paſſage to be ſuppoſititious, becauſe, forſooth, they know not how to ſhape an handſom An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer to it, ſo <hi>Bellarmine,</hi> &amp;c. But others of them, Heretick-like, ſay, <hi>That he did erre, and that one Swallow makes no Summer; and that they regard the practice of your Church, more than the Authority of</hi> Epiphanius. Thus <hi>Salmeron, Sixtus Sinenſis, Gregorius de Valen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia.</hi>
                  <pb n="56" facs="tcp:33762:32"/>But may you thus depreſs the Fathers below your Church? May you thus advance your ſpurious Church above the Fathers, as the Pope doth his Nephews, above Kings and Princes? And may not we prefer the Scriptures above either you or them? But when you have ſaid what you pleaſe, and tryed all the ſhifts you can, yet this Teſtimony of <hi>Epiphanius</hi> is an undeniable evidence againſt you, That the groſs Idolatry of Image-worſhip, how faſt ſoever it was then coming in, yet had not generally prevailed in his time. <hi>Helvicus</hi> placeth him upon the year of Chriſt, 376.</p>
               <p>And ſeeing we are upon this, let us ſee a little further what your Writers ſay of <hi>Epiphanius,</hi> beſide their anger at him for this Teſtimony, what general cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure and character do they give of him? It may be a Divertiſement here, not unpleaſant,
<note place="margin">Can. <hi>Loc. The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ol</hi> lib. 11. p. 477. Rivet. <hi>Critic.</hi> lib. 3. cap. 28. Baron <hi>ad ann. Chriſti</hi> 310. Sect. 15. an. 306. Sect. 45. an. 326. Sect. 4. &amp; 8 an. 327. Sect. 7. ann. 338. Sect. 2. ann. 342. Sect. 50. ann. 306. Sect. 45. ann. 310. Sect 16. Petav. <hi>Ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>madver. ad E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piph.</hi> lib. 1. tom. 1. <hi>ad Hae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſ Samaritan.</hi> pag. 21. <hi>ad. Hae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſ.</hi> 20. <hi>Herodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an.</hi> pag 39. <hi>ad Haereſ. Epicur.</hi> pag. 20.</note> nor unuſeful, to ſee how they handle him, that ſo it may appear whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they have any greater Reverence to the Fathers, than we. <hi>Melchior Canus</hi> ſaith of him, <hi>Nullos ille graves Authores ſequi ſolet. Baronius</hi> is as rude as he, and ſaith, <hi>ab omni ſcopo veritatis abhorrere quod apud Epiphanium legitur falſum item eſſe quod ait,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Rivet</hi> refers the Reader to eight or nine places, wherein he ſhews his judgement freely concerning <hi>Epiphanius.</hi> But <hi>Petavius</hi> the Jeſuite equals, if not exceeds his Fellows, <hi>Permulta enim iſthic falſa</hi> (ſaith he, falſe things) <hi>minimeque cohaerentia diſputat.</hi> And again, <hi>Suſpicamur it aque multipliciter hallucinatum Epiphanium.</hi> And again, in another place, <hi>Totidem paucis illis verbis a ſanctiſſimo eruditiſſimoque viro Epiphanio peccata ſunt. Quorum admonere Lectorem<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> officii eſt institutique nostri, excuſare humanitatis, diſſimulare aut tueri velle, neque officii, neque humanitatis eſt.</hi> So many Errors <hi>(ſaith he)</hi> are here committed in ſo few words, by this holy, and this learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Man <hi>Epiphanius;</hi> of which Errors, to give the Reader warning, is both my Duty and Undertaking in theſe Animadverſions. To excuſe them, is a piece of courteſie and reſpect; but to diſſemble them, or to defend them, is no part ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of Duty or Courteſie. <hi>Thus he.</hi> A ſober, and a well-tempered Speech<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and the more obſervable, becauſe uttered by one that was ſo full of the gall of bitterneſs, as this <hi>Petavius</hi> was. But ſuch Animadverſions, ſuch Reproofs as theſe, have theſe Writers of your own, thought fit to beſtow upon <hi>Epiphanius.</hi> And now, what if we ſhould ſay, that he, as well as ſome other of the Ancients, did hyperbolize, and exceed a little in his Encomiaſticks of St. <hi>Peter;</hi> and that his words and expreſſions are not ſo wary, and ſo well guarded, as they might have been, in predicating the glories of that great Apoſtle. It appears from all this, that we ſhould ſay no worſe of him, nor handle him more unman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerly and irreverently, than your own Writers have done before us:</p>
               <p>This may ſuffice, at preſent, for the further illuſtration of theſe matters. As alſo, for the Vindication of the True Reformed Proteſtant Chriſtian Religion, in the purity of it, as contained in the Holy Scriptures of the Old and New Teſtament, againſt the Roman Catholick Apoſtaſie. <hi>The Lord bleſs what hath been ſaid, for the reducing and bringing home his loſt ſheep, and for the further eſtabliſhment of Believers in their moſt Holy Faith.</hi>
               </p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               <pb facs="tcp:33762:32"/>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
